we would appreciate it
if you are would like to speak, you'll
need to come to either podium
and make sure that the green light comes
on so that everyone that is online will
be able to hear you as well.
Please make sure that you identify
yourself before you make comments
for the record. If you are calling in
virtually today, we want to make sure
that we include you as well. Please make
sure you use the virtual raised hand
feature and
then Jennifer will let you know when
you're able to give your public comment.
Just to let you know there's going to be
a couple of things done differently
today. First and foremost, items number
25, 36, and 37 on the agenda we have to
do with the
property that is um
off of Southwest Drive which may be the
reason some of you are here today.
Is there that developer has asked for
that to be withdrawn. We're not able to
withdraw that as for our normal policy
and procedure. So we will still take a
motion on that but
there will be no second on that so those
will die for lack of a second. That's on
number 25, 36, and 37.
Um
Just want to make sure that
everybody got that, okay? And then we
are going to hear this afternoon
on items number 22, 23, 24, 34, and 35,
which are all related to Microsoft.
We're going to hear that report all at
one time from Microsoft so that they
don't have to come up to the podium six
times. We'll also hear from
Connor White from our planning office
all at one time on those items, and then
we'll address each item individually. So
there will be an opportunity for public
comment as well as for questions from
staff to staff
from the council as well as council
comments on each of those items as they
are in order on the agenda. But we want
to try and make the best use of our time
possible tonight or today.
We do not have a planning commission
happening this evening
in this chambers. So we will make sure
that everyone gets heard today. We are
going to be using a 3-minute timer. And
we would ask that
if you have comments that you would
be brief and try to get all of your
thoughts in out at one time. We will
make sure we that everyone has a chance
to be heard before we let people be
heard a second time on the same topic.
Okay?
Okay, and with that,
Jennifer, if you would read the first
item, please.
>> Number 15, ordinance third reading
amending section 1.3.11
nonconformities, 1.4.4 definitions,
1.4.5
interpretation of zoning map, 2.2.7
special use approval, 5.1.2
zoning districts established, and 5.1.4
use table, and creating 5.6.10
regional entertainment RE overlay
district, and 5.7.13
gaming center development standards, and
setting an effective date for
compliance.
Hey, may we have a staff report, please?
>> Chair, members of the committee, Charles
Bloom, planning and development
director. Um I just passed out a hard
copy of the proposed substitute for this
item. Um so this does have a substitute
that will follow after the main motion
is considered. Uh this is a substitute
that is in line with what was discussed
at the regular meeting of the governing
body on Monday.
It has um three small components. The
major component is it amends uh
attachment or exhibit D, which allows
for this as a special use these uses as
a special use
in the mixed-use business zone district.
You'll see that it reflected in the
exhibit as just the letter S that's
added in the column under mixed-use
business.
Secondly, it modifies the development
standards for the overlay district to
essentially make the separation from
from the places of worship, from child
care centers, and also from recreation
facilities, parks, and schools. Instead
of that being a mandatory criteria, what
it does is it moves it into the required
findings as a new item number 10 for the
special use, which would be applicable
to any type of development that could be
considered by special use. And um it
would be one where it could be evaluated
independently on each scenario. For
example, it may not be appropriate to
limit location of a facility requiring a
special use if it may be less than 500
ft away, but it's on the other side of
an interstate highway, or if it's on the
other side of a a creek or waterway.
Those types of um things. So that's
what's reflected in the substitute. I do
not have any uh comments regarding the
main ordinance and I'm open for any
questions.
>> Here, are there any questions from the
council?
Okay,
we'll go out for public comment then.
[clears throat]
Zoom user, you can unmute yourself.
Please identify yourself.
>> Hi, I just want to make sure I
understand this is about not expanding
the data center, right?
>> This is not we're not on that item. This
is about the recreational
overlay for zoning.
>> Sorry. Okay, I apologize.
>> Go ahead, council.
>> going to say it's in regard to historic
horse racing venues.
>> Tracy Laycock, you can go ahead.
>> I thank you so much, Tracy Laycock,
general counsel for 307 horse racing in
Wyoming Downs.
I I maybe just a point of clarification
through you, chairwoman, if it's okay to
Mr. Bloom.
On the discretionary
criteria, does it then amend the child
care center to an independent building
again or are we keeping that child care
definition the same?
>> Mr. Bloom.
>> Chair, through you to the to the
committee and also
Miss Laycock, that is a great point. It
does. We have changed it to the previous
definite or the previous reference as
introduced to the planning commission,
which means this would be a standalone
facility that's in its own independent
structure and building.
>> I thank you, Mr. Bloom.
Chairwoman, thank you so much for that
that question. We do support uh the
substitute today. Um I just again want
to thank um Mr. Bloom and his office.
They have been exceptional to work with
and this has been a lot of hard work um
but we support um the zoning that the
city is trying to amend along with the
local control bill and uh with the
substitute we support uh
>> [clears throat]
>> the ordinance.
Thank you. I'll stand for any questions.
Thank you.
>> Mr. Miller, are you still able to go
ahead?
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> All right. Um members of the committee,
uh Charles Miller for the record.
I'm initi- This is uh in regards to
auditing the MUB.
Or I mean uh this is
This And also this is uh agenda item
number 15, is that correct?
>> That is correct.
>> Um I am initiating a formal audit of
agenda item number 15 regarding the
regional entertainment overlay district
and gaming center development standards.
>> [gasps]
>> A veracity index of the June 8th City
Council transcript exposes a critical
procedural vulnerability.
The administration is introducing a
substitute today to add gaming centers
as a special use in the mixed-use
business zone.
By the planning director's own admission
on the record, this modification was
drafted to correct an oversight that
would have rendered a currently existing
facility non-compliant.
This is the definition of systemic
arbitrage. The administration is
actively reverse engineering the unified
development code to shield a specific
operating entity from the consequences
of a flawed zoning draft. You are being
asked to retrofit municipal law to
guarantee a predetermined outcome for a
single business rather than establishing
a universal standard for the community.
If the initial presentation to the
planning commission failed to account
for existing zoning conflicts, the
entire architectural framework of this
amendment is compromised. I demand this
committee neutralize this reactionary
exemption. Item 15 must be tabled until
a comprehensive forensic audit proves
that this MUB special use carve out does
not establish a cascading exploitable
loophole across all other mixed-use
business districts in Cheyenne.
We will not codify spot zoning about
>> I don't know what happened to her audio.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can now, yes.
>> Oh,
uh what what was the last thing that you
got there?
>> Codify is where I lost you.
>> Oh.
Um
uh spot zoning by We will not codify
spot zoning by proxy. Thanks.
>> Thank you.
Any other comments online, Jennifer?
Any other comments here in the room?
Okay, hearing none or seeing none, I
would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I would move that we
um
approve on third reading.
>> Second.
>> Here we have a motion by Dr. Rennie, a
second by Dr. Immens.
>> Madam Chairwoman.
>> Uh Dr. Rennie.
>> I move to amend by substitute and the
print is too small on the substitute,
but it looks like it's dated today.
>> June 15th at 8:35 a.m.
>> Second.
>> So, we have
a substitute that uh motion to
substitute uh dated June 15th, 2026 by
Dr. Rennie, seconded by Dr. Immens.
Um
is there any public comment on
that modification or the substitute?
>> Uh Madam Chairwoman, I'm Mark Boone
Shay, City Council, Ward 3. I support
it. Seems like it actually gives us more
control over these. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Any other public comments about the
substitute?
Anyone online?
Okay, hearing none or seeing none.
Um, any discussion from the
>> Madam Chairwoman.
>> Yes.
>> Speaking for the amendment, the omission
of MEU
the lack of MEU MEUB being in the
original draft was a simple omission by
our staff. It was our intent always
that um
the existing
venues be grandfathered at least for the
next 3 years before their review.
>> Thank you for that clarification. Dr.
Rennie.
Any other comments, questions by the
committee?
Okay, hearing none. All in favor of the
substitute say I.
>> I.
>> Okay, this item um it now is the
substitute, so we'll go back to the
original motion.
Um, any discussion from the committee on
the original motion?
Hearing none. All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
Okay, this item will move forward uh to
the council on next Monday night. Next
item, please.
>> Number 16, ordinance third reading
amending chapter 15.20 National
Electrical Code adopted appendix K
International Building Code
administrative provisions adopted of
title 15 buildings and construction of
the municipal code of the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming updating the
incorporated National Electrical Code
provisions as specified.
>> May we have a staff report, please?
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
uh Anthony Parmelo, Chief Building
Official, City of Cheyenne.
What you have before you is the adoption
of the 2026 National Electrical Code. Um
currently we have um had no comments
received from citizens on the adoption.
We have had or held our open house on
the 28th. Um we had uh minimal
attendance. One individual had some
questions which we were able to answer.
Um we really don't have any more
comments than that and we have met all
uh statutory required um meetings and
notice for the adoption of this code. I
stand for any questions.
>> Thank you. Are there any questions from
the committee for Mr.
Carmelo?
Okay, thank you, sir.
Any public comment?
We're on item 16.
All right, no none online.
Okay.
Seeing none or hearing none, um
I would entertain a motion.
>> Um Madam Chairwoman, I move to approve
on third and final reading.
>> Second.
>> Okay, we have a motion from Dr. Emmons
and a second from Councilman Laybourn.
Um any discussion?
All in favor, say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
This item will move on for to the
council on third and final reading. Next
item, please.
>> Number 17, ordinance second reading
annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming land located south of Charles
Street, east of Winandy Avenue, and west
of McKinley Avenue.
>> Okay, if we can have a staff report,
please.
>> Chair, members of the committee, this is
Anthony Kobalniky, Planning and
Development Department. This annexation
is for roughly 2.69 acres of land
generally located south of Charles
Street, east of Winandy Avenue, and west
of McKinley Avenue.
The land proposed is to be annexed is
contiguous to the current city limits.
Specifically, the property is 72%
contiguous.
All city services and utilities
currently available to residents of the
city will be provided to the residents
of the annexed land. Extending water and
sewer will increase the health and
safety of the residents living in this
area of the community.
The area to be annexed is partly inside
the urban service boundary and
designated as mixed-use residential by
the future land use map.
This type of development is best
supported by being within city limits
and by connecting the city services.
A certified mailing was sent to all
landowners and utilities
within the annexed area not less than 20
business days prior to the public
hearing.
According to the city's calendar, 20
business days prior to today's hearing
was May 12th, 2026.
The certified mailing was sent out on
May 8th, 2026.
And the earliest confirmation of receipt
was dated May 11th, 2026.
Property owners within 300 ft of the
subject property were also mailed public
notice within this same time period. The
This annexation is accompanied by an
assigned zoning ordinance.
>> Thank you.
Is there any Are there any questions
from committee?
>> Over to Connor for questions.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay. Nice job. Thank you.
Okay, any public comment?
Anyone online?
Okay, hearing
no public comment, seeing no hands
raised for virtual comments,
um
I would entertain a motion.
>> So moved.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Councilman
Laybourne, a second from Dr. Renny. Um
to approve. Is there any discussion?
All in favor, say I.
>> I.
>> It is added and we'll move forward with
recommendation to approve.
Next item, please.
Number 18, ordinance second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne and the zoning
classification of AR agricultural
residential for land annexed to the city
of Cheyenne located south of Charles
Street, east of Winandy Avenue, and west
of McKinley Avenue.
So, as with any piece of land that we
annex, we do have to give it a zone, and
so we'll have a staff report on that.
>> Madam Chair, members of the board, this
is an assigned zoning for an owner
petitioned annexation at 5631 Charles
Street. The current zoning is county
land use. This zone allows for a variety
of uses. The future land use map
designates this area as mixed-use
residential.
The current use of the property is
Lots that are similar in size and
location have been zoned AR agricultural
residential.
While the current use may not involve
agricultural activities, the parcel is
large enough to sustain limited
agricultural uses and should be zoned to
accommodate those potential uses.
The planning commission heard this at
their June 1st meeting and recommends
approval.
>> Thank you. Any questions from committee?
Okay, we'll go out for public comment.
This is on the zoning of that piece of
property that we just annexed.
Okay.
Uh Jennifer.
Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> I can.
>> All right, and this is number 18,
correct?
>> That's correct.
>> Uh Madam Chair, committee members, for
the record, Charles Miller.
Um my comments are strictly germane to
item 18, the ordinance establishing the
AR agricultural residential zoning
classification
for the land located south of Charles
Street and east of Winandy Avenue.
Because this zoning amendment is
inextricably linked to the annexation of
this exact same parcel. Approving item
18 carries the exact same catastrophic
uh
district court liabilities
placed
on the record here. Uh
this is uh first is the jurisdictional
nudity.
Um
it appears that the city failed the
20-business-day statutory notice
requirement. Um
If Oh, I'm sorry.
You've got
I apologize. [snorts]
Give me just 1 moment here. I'm sorry.
I'm sorry. Did you uh Could you guys
please give me the uh
the notice period that was provided to
uh the surrounding areas?
>> It I believe that May 12th was the date
and we received notification that
someone had received that mailing on May
11th. That first
um
recognition of that mailing.
>> Uh I'm sorry. When when was it first uh
sent out?
>> Madam Chair, Conway Planning Development
Department. So, the notice requirement
is for the annexation for the public
hearing, not specifically today's
meeting.
Um so, with the public hearing that was
held last Monday, we have to send out
mailed notice 20 days 20 business days
prior to.
Um we sent it out
I want to say that was May 8th or 7th,
one of the two.
Um 20 business days
was around the 8th. Um so, we did meet
statutory requirements for mailed notice
to all landowners. The assigned zoning,
again, as a reminder for everybody,
assigned zoning goes with the annexation
because we have to give a zone to a
property that is annexed. The way that
is on the agenda, we would approve the
annexation, then you would approve the
assigned zoning. So, it is in order
that it would need to be for any
assigned zoning giving a zone to land
that is then annexed.
>> And we did meet the statutory
requirement for notification for the
public hearing.
>> Correct. We met the statutory
requirements.
>> Okay, thank you.
>> Okay.
Any other public comment?
Okay.
Hearing none or seeing none, I would
entertain a motion.
>> So moved.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Councilman
Leybourn, a second from Councilman
Renneisen. Any discussion?
All in favor, say aye.
This item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve. Next item,
please.
>> Number 19, ordinance second reading
annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming land northwest of the
intersection of Clear Creek Parkway and
Gannett Peak Drive.
>> Staff report, please.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
Carter White, Planning and Development
Department.
So, the annexation before you, it's for
roughly 26 acres of land. This is out in
the Swan Ranch
Business Park area. It's off of Clear
Creek Parkway.
This annexation is um
basically proposed
to come into the city to be added to
additional land. So, there is multiple
parts to this that you'll see the same
parcel.
Um
So, with this we do have the assigned
zoning, and there's a zone change as
well for a lot larger of the area than
just this parcel. And then you'll see
next week a plat be introduced as well.
With the annexation,
uh this parcel is
um
over 50% contiguous to city limits. So,
you do have city limits on the west side
and then the south and then a little bit
towards the southwest.
Um
with this annexation,
it's uh basically proposed again to be
added to to additional land and it's
part of a sale.
There's already utilities out here um in
the Swan Ranch area.
Uh so, they won't have to be extended
very far.
We did again with this meet the
statutory requirement for mailed notice.
Uh it did go all the property owners
within 300 ft
um as well as utilities and uh the
applicant as well.
This did have its public hearing last
week. Uh there's been no public comment
on this item. Staff has received no
specific emails related to this item as
well or phone calls.
Uh and with that, staff does recommend
approval and I'm available for any
questions.
>> Hey, um Dr. Emmons.
Thank you, Madam Chair.
Uh just to be clear, this is an owner
request.
>> Madam Chair, through you to Dr. Emmons,
yes, this is an owner uh initiated
annexation.
>> Thank you.
Any other questions from committee?
Hearing and seeing none, we'll go out to
the audience for any comments, public
comments.
Nice to see you, Mark.
>> Good afternoon, Chair, uh members of the
committee. My name is Mark Christensen.
I am with AVI here in Cheyenne. Um so,
as staff had mentioned, this is a
owner-initiated application uh for
annexation.
Um this will be an expansion of the Swan
Ranch uh business park. Um so, this
annexation is requested to accompany the
the platting action and the zoning
action uh for future industrial type
development and I'm available for any
questions.
>> Thank you.
Any other public comment?
Anything online, Jennifer? I don't see
anything.
Okay.
I would entertain uh hearing none I Oh,
sorry. Mr. Miller.
Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
Mr. Miller, we see your hand raised, but
it shows that you're still muted.
>> Um I apologize. I'm experiencing some
technical difficulties. I'm going to
have to um
just move on to the next. Uh so, thank
you.
>> Thank you.
Okay, any other public comment?
Hearing none or seeing none, I would
entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairman,
Madam Chairwoman, I would so move or
move to approve on second reading.
>> Okay, we have a motion from Councilman
Rinne, a second from Dr. Emmons.
Um
and we are on item 19.
Um any discussion?
All in favor, say aye.
>> Aye.
>> Okay, this item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve on Monday
night.
Um we will now go on to item number 20
and give this piece of property a a
zone.
So, number 20, ordinance second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne establishing the zoning
classification of LI, light industrial,
for land annexed to the city of Cheyenne
located northwest of the intersection of
Clear Creek Parkway and Gannett Peak
Drive. Staff report, please, Mr. White.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
Carrolway Planning and Development
Department.
So, as mentioned, uh with any
annexation, we do have to give it a
city's own when it's uh annexed,
otherwise it has no zoning in the city.
So, with this assigned zoning, we did
take a look at what the current county
zone is. The current county zone is
actually light industrial.
Um
this whole area is generally either
light industrial or a planned unit
development. That planned unit
development is mainly a heavy industrial
planned unit development. Uh it's
basically written in a way that
basically just allows heavy industrial
uses with a lot less requirements. Um or
not a lot less requirements, but a lot
less landscaping requirements.
Um
so upon staff's review of the assigned
zoning, we do recommend that this
property be assigned the LI zone. That
would allow it to basically use or have
the same uses it would be allowed in the
county upon annexation.
And also the light again, light
industrial zone is
basically the major zone district that
is currently out in this area. Uh so
with that, I am available for any
questions. I should note, I guess,
planning commission did hear this item
on June 1st. They did recommend approval
of this item on June 1st as well. So I'm
available for any questions.
>> Are there any questions for staff?
Hey, any public comment?
Hey, hearing none or seeing none, I
Okay, go ahead, Dr. Rennie. Did you have
a question?
>> No, ma'am. I was ready to make a motion.
>> Okay. Dr. Rennie.
I would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I'd move to approve on
second reading.
>> Okay, we have a motion from Dr. Rennie,
a second from Dr. Immens
um to approve. Any discussion?
All in favor, say I.
Okay, this item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve at the next
council meeting.
Um next item, please. Do you have a
number?
>> Number 21, ordinance second reading
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located north
and south of West Walek Road and west of
Interstate 25 from LI, light industrial,
CB, community business, and PUD, planned
unit development, to BP, business park.
Staff report, please.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
Connor Way, Planning and Development
Department.
The item before you, um as I had noted,
uh there was a couple items that went
around went with this annexation.
Um this portion does contain
more than just the annexed area. Uh with
our BP zone, you are required to have
320 acres to even be able to establish
the BP zone.
Um
so
what the applicant has uh presented
is this larger area. It does incorporate
that annexed land.
Um
E
as we've had discussions on the BP zone
over the past couple months, um the BP
zone is a mix of both the LI, HI, and CB
zone.
Um with the land that is proposed to be
rezoned, it incorporates the LI zone.
There is a community business parcel as
well on the
uh east side of Clear Creek, closer to
I-25. And then it does incorporate some
parcels that are within that PUD that I
had mentioned that is mainly a heavy
industrial PUD.
With the BP zone,
um
it gives that flexibility of being able
to have a mix a lot more mix of uses.
Um
as we've also had the discussion, it
does kind of loosen up the landscaping
requirements slightly. Uh landscaping is
still required on every parcel in the BP
zone. It does just loosen it up and
requires a lot less trees, so we aren't
getting massive
uh forests planted on some of these
larger parcels.
Um ultimately, uh one of the biggest
benefits is just making it so that you
don't have to constantly rezone back and
forth between the various zone
districts.
Um and it allows a lot more uh variety
of uses between
having some of those CB uses, the LI
uses, and the HI uses.
Looking at the area, this is an
industrial area uh industrial industrial
area. Uh so the BP zone does fit in.
Um
again, with it being an industrial-type
zone.
Also, uh they do meet the 320-acre
requirement.
Uh with the number of parcels and land
that is proposed to be rezoned.
Planning Commission did hear this item
um at their June 1st meeting, and they
did recommend approval of the zoning map
amendment.
And with that, I am available for any
questions.
>> Any questions from committee?
Okay, we'll go out for public comment.
Is there anyone here in the room who
would like to make public comment?
Mr. Christensen.
>> Madam Chair, through you, my name is
Mark Christensen. I'm with AVI here in
Cheyenne. Um so, just wanted to
reiterate that uh we support the the
staff report on this item. Um the item
was submitted just as the BP zone is a
combination of the LI, HI, and CB zone
districts, uh which uh if you look at
the zoning map there, they're all over
in this area. So, uh we thought it would
be best to consolidate the different
types of uses that are allowed in these
three zones into the BP zone. Um and
with that, I'm available for any
questions.
>> Thank you, sir.
Any other public comment or any
questions?
Any public comment here in the room?
Okay, I
go ahead.
Ms. Madrid.
>> Hi, Heather Madrid. I just I more have a
question.
Um
I'm what I wonder why some
county properties are annexed into the
city and are and right away annexed
appropriately
for like this one is going to be, you
know, in in a business park and was
zoned light industrial ahead of time,
but others are
annexed and then zoned into agricultural
instead of
what they're actually going to be long
term. I don't under I under I guess I
understand the need to rezone, so you
know, but I don't understand why some
why why aren't we treating them all the
same?
>> That is a great question and in I I
think I can give you that answer is that
when we annex um a piece of property
from the county into the city, we try
and give it as similar zone. Um because
every piece of property would need to be
zone have a city zone. And we so we try
and give it a similar zone. So if it was
a piece of agricultural land, um then
the zone unless it's been asked for in
another action by the property owner
would come in as agricultural or
whatever the closest zone is to that
county zone that it currently has. And
then there would be another process to
change the zone.
Is that did I do a good job?
>> And I'm not sure I can also add to that
kind of It's more the way that our
department also looks at it's it's a
backup zone. Um cuz I know this is
probably going to come up with
I think it's the next item on the agenda
with the larger annexation, why why is
staff recommending that be zoned ag to
begin with when we know that they want
to build the data center.
The reason is if council annexes it,
zones it ag, and then doesn't zone it
BP, it has a city zone. It has a backup
zone. Otherwise, we're annexing a parcel
not giving it a zone.
Well, then what do we do with no zone
district?
They basically have no regulation.
So we have to have that backup zone,
which is why we always have an assigned
zoning to whatever's closest to
surrounding zoning, surrounding uses,
what is in the county,
uh what the land is being used as.
So, that's ultimately what that assigned
zoning is. It's It's a backup zone in
case
somebody does request a different zone
district and that zone district fails.
>> Is that answered? Okay.
Okay.
Any other comments?
Okay, and I see Mr. Miller has his hand
up.
Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Uh Madam Chair, committee members, for
the record, Charles Miller.
My comments are strictly germane to item
number 21, the ordinance amending the
zoning classification for the land
located north and south of West Walcott
Road to a business park.
Um
approving this item [clears throat]
today exposes the city
to catastrophic district court liability
due to bad faith jurisdictional
arbitrage and an egregious documented
financial conflict of interest. Defect
number one, confessed jurisdictional
arbitrage. Your own planner, Connor
White, just stated on a live microphone
that this boundary was presented
specifically because the applicant is
required to hit 320 acres to establish
the BP zone.
During the June 1st Planning Commission
hearing, the applicant's agent, Mark
Christensen, formally admitted on the
public record that they are stringing
together some other properties simply to
meet this minimum.
This is a confessed bad faith
gerrymandering of the municipal zoning
map designed specifically to create a
regulatory loophole.
Uh defect number two, the state siting
bypass.
Uh by rubber stamping this fabricated
business park contiguity, you are
actively facilitating the evasion of the
Wyoming Industrial Siting Act. This
intentional circumvention illegally
strips Laramie County of the
state-mandated socioeconomic impact fees
we desperately need to protect our
infrastructure.
Furthermore, the state legislature is
actively pulling right now
for a special session to address this
exact type of regulatory evasion.
Defect number three, the Wallick Road
conflict of interest.
The agent lobbying for this massive
industrial rezoning on West Wallick Road
is AVI Professional Corporation. Yet,
official city documents prove that this
city just awarded a $252,522
taxpayer-funded contract to AVI
Professional Corporation specifically to
conduct the Wallick Road extension
feasibility study. You're utilizing a
quarter million dollars in public tax
funds to pay the developer's agent to
study the exact same road where they're
actively lobbying this committee for an
industrial rezoning.
This financial entanglement irreparably
taints this entire quasi-judicial
proceeding and violates the public
trust. You cannot legally approve a
gerrymandered zone
change while simultaneously funneling a
quarter million dollars to the
applicant's agent to study the exact
same road. I strongly advise a no vote.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Are there any other public
comments? Yes, ma'am.
Just My name is Jana Tolman. I'm from
Indian Hills.
Um
it just seems that
it is zoned for one
type of zoning to another type of zoning
to another type of zoning for the of
I don't know. Is this for another data
center?
Um
is is that the purpose of of the
rezoning?
Um I don't know. As watching through all
these things that are being very quickly
approved of, it just seems like
we need some planning committee to begin
looking at different ways in which we
can
sell out a plan for Cheyenne that it
doesn't have a something here and
something there and
it just seems just very scattered and
I don't know.
Just
for a lot of
taxpayers, we just don't understand you
know, what's going on until it's too
late. Uh because we don't understand all
these different zoning and planning
codes and that sort of thing.
And I would just like us to
look a little bit more in detail at how
we can
best
um
plan for future prosperity and
that it won't affect the
the residents as much.
Um we're
zoning into business park
a lot of of this area and
um I just want to know how much
of Cheyenne is going to become business
park
um zones.
How much of it is going to be
be used for that use because um
it just seems like we're putting a lot
of different things for
you know, big entities which is going to
affect the taxpayers.
Especially we don't know if they're
going to be exempt from paying taxes. We
don't know what kind of revenue we're
going to get. We're just approving.
And so I don't know. I'd like to see
some sort of planning committee
and that it be brought forth in a way
that taxpayers can understand what's
going on.
>> Thank you, Ms. Tolman.
Mr. White.
>> And just re- just reminded everyone
we're talking about this business park.
We're not
>> Business park, yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> I also don't live too far from that
business park where you're talk- talking
about. I looked on a map, there's a
school right next to that area. After I
can't pronounce that word, but it's a
elementary school.
And
my question is, how many data centers
are we going to have in Cheyenne?
The The question is, we already have
some already. Are we competing against
other cities or other countries? Is that
what's going on?
You have you ever listened to your own
people, Cheyenne, that what they Some
don't like the data center. We got
enough already. How many more of these
industrial places you're going to build?
Building data center. Now, if you're
building something like Walmart, the
distribution center, that's a little
different. Data center, AI center, it's
a whole different ballgame. Around this
country, people are fighting against
this data center. If you're not aware of
it, you need to start looking. I have a
friend that's a native, he's an actor,
he's in Kansas fighting against data
center. I ain't the only one, either.
We just as people, you guys got to
support the people here in Cheyenne that
lives here. You guys are supporting
people that are coming in, building it,
the workers and everything that works
here, they're going to be gone.
To run a data center, you don't need
that many people running the data
center.
I'm just trying to let you guys know,
you guys need to wake up. Listen to your
people in Cheyenne.
And also listen to people that live out
in the county.
I noticed that you guys are assizing a
lot of land around this area. You
promised some of these people
I won't mention any certain things they
still can't do, and you threw a rule on
them.
You know, some of us that live out in
the country reason for our live out in
the country so we do what we want and
live freedom.
When the city steps in, that's
government.
Government starts controlling.
As you can see, I'm Native American. I
understand what government does,
controlling. It happens on the
reservation and all over.
And I'm just saying thing now it's it's
no longer the reservation. Now it's the
people that are residents like in
Cheyenne. There's all these government
laws that you could put out. It's also
include the national government. There's
law on top law, then you put another law
on top of that law that pushing this
other law.
Do Do I make myself clear? I'm getting
sick and tired of this data center cuz I
got one that near my house. They drilled
two wells. Just hear me out.
And I've been watching my water
pressure.
For example, they told me there's a
aquifer water right here. They're going
to drill. Down below there's another
water. What happens in between that? How
do we trust what goes in between that
where they drill?
You know, what if that water comes back
into our aquifer water? We don't know
what kind of water that is underneath
that water.
That that at the time they'll say yes or
I don't trust corporation. They lie.
They lie every time. They'll just get
their business in so they could get, you
know, their business built. Mandate I
mean making imitating pretend I can't
remember that word, but
making people believe what they're
saying. Someone's got to wake up because
some of these corporates are
I'm done. Okay. [laughter]
But I just thought I just thought I'd
speak my peace because it's bothering me
a lot. And that one more thing, if we
don't watch how many data centers going
to bite us in the butt already. And
they're already starting to have cameras
in your new vehicles watching what you
do. Is that freedom? No, that's
invasion.
>> Thank you, Mr. White.
>> Okay.
>> Any other public comment?
Okay, hearing none. I would entertain a
motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I would have moved to
approve on second reading.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Dr. Renny and a
second from Dr. Emmons.
Um is there any discussion?
>> Madam Chair, I'm going to I just want to
point out that
at least this request is on the west
side of the interstate
and I don't see a school anywhere nearby
there.
>> Okay, thank you.
Um any other discussion?
All in favor say I.
Okay, this item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve on Monday
evening.
Okay, just a reminder, if you came
because we did have some people come in
a little late. Um if you are here for
item number 25, 36, or 37, um that is
with the property off of Southwest
Drive. That developer has asked for that
to be um voted down um so that
um they can regroup and have some more
community meetings is my understanding.
Um so if you're here for those items, we
will be making a motion and um those
will be um most likely dying for lack of
a second. Um we are now getting ready to
go into item number 22 and if you came
in late, you may want to hear this that
item number 22, 23, 24, 34, and 35 all
have to do with Microsoft. Um they're
going to do one presentation. Our staff
will then give an overall presentation
and then we're going to take each item
individually. So you'll still have an
opportunity to make comments
individually on each item. Um but that
way Microsoft is just doing one
presentation and our staff will um
do one overall presentation and then
they'll also um do a presentation of
each individual item and break it down.
So um we'll go ahead and Jennifer, if
you'd like to read
um just item number 22 into the record
and then they'll do their presentation.
>> Number 22, ordinance second reading,
annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming, land east of South Greeley
Highway and south of Sweetgrass
subdivision.
>> Thank you.
Mr. Emmons.
>> Uh Madam Chairwoman, uh Brad Emmons and
uh committee members, Brad Emmons AVI
agent for the owner, Arpan Emmond
Hardware Company, Old Horse Pasture
Incorporated, and and Lammas Livestock
LLC, and the
uh developer of the property, uh
Microsoft. Um they're looking at This is
an owner-initiated annexation. The
annexation is 3,459.99
acres of land. Um they will be
this uh as you will see as we move
forward, the zone changes it for a
smaller area as the Lammas family is
keeping parts of that that area under
their control and leaving it AG zone.
So, as
the assigned zoning goes through,
there'll be part of it that will stay
AG, and then part of it that would be
requested to go to BP
um as we move forward. Um
We did have an open house with the
neighbors, all the adjacent neighbors,
and the people in the Grass Hill
subdivision, which is the nearest
housing subdivision to the southeast.
Um
before the planning commission member
meeting, we had three members of that
subdivision attend, ask questions, and
uh had a question and answer at that, um
and did not get any additional comments
from them after that meeting.
Um
as we move forward, Microsoft does would
like to uh develop this property within
the city limits. That That's why they're
uh applying for the annexation. Um they
believe it's the best to be on public
water and sewer um and to follow this
the process through the city rules and
regulations.
Um so, happy to answer your questions on
any of those five items as we move
forward. Um we will have a separate 26,
28, and 29 on the other property just to
as a reminder then a Microsoft property
as well. So,
>> Thank you.
>> Yep. I'll turn it over to Microsoft.
>> Okay.
>> Good afternoon, Chair, members of the
committee. For the record, my name is
Rachel Erwin, land development and
permitting program manager for the
Cheyenne region.
Our address is one Microsoft Way,
Redmond, Washington.
Today's request includes three actions
for Highlands. Annexation into the city
of Cheyenne, rezoning the property to
business park, and a future land use
amendment.
I'd like to give a quick overview of the
project. Highlands is a 3,050 acre
property with an existing Microsoft
campus and planned conservation area to
the west, gravel pits to the north, a
planned solar farm to the east, and
state land to the south.
I do want to note that Microsoft does
not yet own this property.
The site is currently going through our
acquisition process, and these
applications are part of early stage
planning. With that being said, we are
working to close on this property in the
coming weeks.
Because of this, our goal here today is
transparency. I've brought a few of our
subject matter experts with me today
from our water, wastewater, energy, and
community affairs team
so that we can do our absolute best to
answer any questions that you may have.
And also be clear about what we know
today and what we will know
in the future as our project is refined
and progresses.
That same approach to transparency is
how we've been engaging with the
community as well.
On May 27th, as Brad was stating, we did
hold a neighborhood meeting for the
those surrounding the Highland property,
where we had the opportunity to answer
questions directly.
The following day, on May 28th, we did
host a public community open house that
had roughly 150 attendees, where we
shared our expansion plans and had
subject matter experts available to
respond to any questions.
We plan to continue those community
engagements throughout the summer to
ensure residents have the opportunity to
bring forward questions and concerns
because we do want community and city
input
um
to be involved in the shaping of our
plans moving forward.
One of the most consistent questions
we've heard to date is why is the site
so large and why are these approvals
being requested now?
Highlands is a long-term planning
effort.
Um, not an immediate full build-out of
the campus. Development of this site may
occur over 10 to 20 years as
infrastructure, technology, and demand
evolve.
And while you may not see work directly
on the property in the near term, that
does not mean that work wouldn't have
begun.
Uh, that site likely will require
significant off-site improvements
including what utility, roadway, and
power upgrades which we anticipate
advancing ahead of any vertical data
center construction to properly support
future development.
Planning at the full parcel scale allows
Microsoft and the city to work
holistically on these infrastructure
improvements rather than approaching
these decisions in a fragmented way over
time. It also allows the city into the
process significantly earlier when those
decisions can still be shaped
collaboratively.
Annexation ensures that this project be
developed under city standards and
within city jurisdiction allowing for
coordinated planning with the city and
the Board of Public Utilities. With that
in mind, we believe these actions
establish the right framework for
responsible long-term planning while
still preserving future review as more
details are defined.
Thank you for your time. From here, I'd
like to invite our water subject matter
experts to the podium to speak to
infrastructure planning and answer any
questions that you may have. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Good afternoon, Madam Chair and members
of the committee.
For the record, my name is Dewey Wynn
and I serve as the water and waste water
program manager for Microsoft in the
Cheyenne region.
Our address is one Microsoft Way,
Redmond, Washington.
For this Highlands site, raw water and
waste water infrastructure requirements
have been covered with Wopu as part of
our initial due diligence process and
it's mutually agreed that the project,
Microsoft's project, can be supported.
In cooperation with the Cheyenne Board
of Public Utilities, the infrastructure
will be delivered to enable continued
growth for the surrounding area.
And all planning, detailed design, and
construction of the infrastructure will
be 100% funded by Microsoft.
All planning, design, and construction
of the infrastructure will also be
performed in collaboration with Cheyenne
Board of Public Utilities and our local
development partners such as Leads and
AVI.
The infrastructure will be developed in
phases to support our phase full site
development.
And with that, I'm available for
questions.
>> Thank you.
>> Good afternoon, Madam Chair, and
committee members. My name is Tyler
Gibbs.
I am with Microsoft Corporation. I am
senior manager
of energy markets for Microsoft, focus
primarily here on Cheyenne,
enabling our
growth. As we know, data centers do
require a lot of electricity, so that is
my sole job.
As you can see on this slide, one of the
things that's very beneficial about
Cheyenne is that we have
worked in partnership with Black Hills
Energy, developed a large power contract
service, really which
um
is a means of ensuring that there's
ratepayer protection,
that the decisions we make
will not impact other customers' rates.
Um and generally, when data centers
enter a region, it actually can bring
down costs for other ratepayers.
Uh one of the a couple of interest
interesting things about the LPCS, one
of them, it does require us to directly
pay for 100% of the infrastructure
upgrades that are required to support
our
uh growth and our data centers.
We have to pay for 100% of the power
that's procured or generated to provide
electricity to our data centers.
The The thing that's unique about this
tariff is that it does enable the
utility to call on our backup generators
in the event of a grid emergency. So, if
market power is tight or there's some
generation outages in the region,
utility has the option to call on
Microsoft to shed load to backup
generators before curtailing hospitals,
nursing homes, schools,
and other base retail and commercial
customers.
We'll also look to continue to bring
additional generation and capacity onto
the market,
many of which of those technologies are
not water intensive.
Um and then last but not least, I wanted
to share one of the interesting and and
fun things I enjoy about my job here, uh
and I'm located in Ward 2, by the way,
is that uh
some of our contractual terms of our
previous power procurement agreements
and what we plan to do in the future too
and entails including some community
benefits.
Uh so, we partnered with Black Hills,
NextEra, and Southern Power to pledge
$1.3 million to the Boys & Girls Club of
Cheyenne over 10 years.
And uh
that was a picture from the event and
something I really enjoy about the job.
Here for your questions.
>> Good afternoon, chair and members of the
committee.
My name's Lucas Downey, and I serve as a
community affairs manager with
Microsoft.
I appreciate the opportunity to be
before you today.
I want to begin by returning to
something I've had the chance to share
before, Microsoft's community first
commitments. These are five concrete
promises Microsoft has made to the
communities where we build, own, and
operate our data centers.
I think it's important to have these on
the public record here in Cheyenne, so
I'd like to read them aloud.
One, we'll pay our own way to ensure our
data centers don't increase your
electricity prices.
Two,
we'll minimize our water use and
replenish more of your water than we
use.
Three, we'll create jobs for your
residents.
Four,
will add to the tax base for your local
hospitals, schools, parks, and
libraries. And five, will strengthen
your community by investing in local
training and nonprofits.
Those five commitments are not
aspirational language. Those are the
standards we hold ourselves to.
Okay, perfect. I know how to work the
thing.
Um and you can see that commitment in
action. Since 2018, Microsoft has
supported 56 community projects across
28 local organizations, donated 4.7
million dollars to local nonprofits and
programs. We are proud to support over
50 local initiatives,
including the Boys and Girls Club,
LCCC's Data Center Academy,
Rooted in Cheyenne, the Wyoming Women's
Business Center, Habitat for Humanity,
and the Cheyenne Frontier Days, among
many others.
From steam education to digital skills
training to ecological restoration,
we're investing in the full fabric of
the community.
That community investment is backed by
real economic impact. This slide
reflects an independent analysis by
Ernst & Young.
Since 2019, our operations here have
generated 1.6 billion dollars in
economic activity and 285 million in
local labor income, supporting 320
direct Microsoft jobs, and over 1,000
on-site contractors and additional jobs.
On the construction side, we have added
another 1.4 billion in economic activity
and 3,900 local jobs.
For every one operations job at a
Microsoft data center, 4.4 additional
jobs are created across local businesses
in this community.
Microsoft has been in Cheyenne since
2012. We're here for the long term, and
these numbers reflect that commitment.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Okay, staff report.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
Conor Wade, planning and development
department. So, we have a couple of
various different items
uh with this one project.
So, we have an annexation.
Again, with annexation, we have an
assigned zoning, and then we have an
applicant requested zone change, and
then also an applicant requested future
land use map amendment. Uh there is
another item on here
uh which I'll go over a little bit more
detail is basically that overruling of
the planning commission's determination
for the future land use map amendment.
Starting with the annexation,
um yes, this is a roughly 3,500 acre
annexation.
Um this does incorporate land that
you'll notice when
I kind of flip through
uh some of these um
basically pages I pulled up or PDFs.
The rezoning does not cover the entire
3,500 acres.
Uh so, basically the annexation does
incorporate land that is not part of
what is being proposed to be rezoned to
business park.
Um
with the annexation,
um one of the things is
having kind of the pre-discussion on
this, staff did ask if
we could basically have the additional
land annexed with what Microsoft wanted
to purchase and develop, otherwise we'd
be creating county pockets.
And we know how that has gone when we've
got county pockets. Uh granted, it's all
one landowner out here.
Um so, they were more than happy to also
annex those pieces.
But,
um with this annexation,
uh
the land is
around, I want to say 46% contiguous, so
a large portion is contiguous with city
limits.
Um you do have Bison Business Park that
is to the
southwest. Uh Sweetgrass is kind of
north and uh northwest.
And then yes, you do have the county a
little bit to the north
um
east and then
also to the east, southeast, and a
little bit to the south is also the
county as well.
With this annexation, um
they will need to extend water and
sewer.
Um as Microsoft had mentioned, that is
fully funded by them. They would be the
ones who would have to construct that
construct utilities and bring them into
this area.
Um BOPU has stated that it is
serviceable.
Um
yes, it's going to take a little bit of
design,
uh but it is a serviceable area. They
can extend the utilities to the area.
Again, with the annexation, um
it had mailed notice
to all property owners who are within
300 ft. Um
we haven't had any comments.
Um
at the beginning with this, we did end
up with an email over the weekend
uh that was just a
general email not liking the Microsoft
uh developments
um in general, but that's been the only
other public comment we've received um
basically since the public hearing.
With again with annexations, uh we do
have
this to go.
We do have the assigned zoning.
This assigned zoning would cover this
entire parcel. Um
looking at how large the parcel is and
looking at
um
basically uses and everything else,
staff does recommend the AG zone for the
assigned zoning. As I stated before,
basically the assigned zoning acts as
that backup zone. So, if council chose
to annex this property, assign it the AG
zone, but then not approve the business
park zone district, at least we have an
annexed parcel that has
city zoning attached to it.
Um
right now, my understanding with the
land,
there's an oil field on the property,
but otherwise it's ranch land.
Um it's open.
So,
looking at that and looking at the
surrounding area, that's why staff would
recommend the AG zone.
Um at the June 1st Planning Commission
meeting, Planning Commission did
recommend approval of that AG zone.
Um
so,
moving on to the next item, which this
one I'm going to speak about
both the future land use map and the
zone change together.
Um
as basically these two items do go
together.
The zoning map amendment, um it is being
requested by the applicant to change
just over 3,000 acres to the BP zone.
So, as you can see
um on this map,
it is not the full extent of what is
being annexed.
So, if I flip back through these, I'll
try to go slowly,
you can see that
it changes.
Um
they're only requesting the BP zone for
what they plan to purchase and develop.
With the BP zone,
as again, as we've discussed over the
past several months, it is a mix of
various zone districts.
Uh the BP zone, cuz I've been hearing
this comment come up, everybody thinks
that BP is just related to data centers.
Data centers are allowed in more than
just the BP zone as a use by right.
Um so, in the LI zone, they're use by
right. HI zone, use by right.
CB zone, I believe they're a conditional
use.
Um MUB zone, they're also a conditional
Data centers are allowed in a lot more
than just the BP zone. Yes, they are
used by right in the BP zone and a lot
of uh these ones we've seen, they've
been requesting the BP.
Uh but they're also in this case, this
is adjacent to the BP zone within the
city.
So, down in this corner,
this is Bison Business Park.
That has been zoned by the council as
BP.
So, BP zoning is already in the area.
This is an extension of that BP zone.
Additionally, uh which I believe
everybody was given that map from Leads
at the last council meeting. I actually
have a digital copy
as well.
Um looking at this area, there is a
gravel pit that's out here. There is to
the east, you do have oil fields.
To the southeast, you have a large uh
solar farm that is planned and Best
Project.
And then, state lands are further to the
south.
So, already out in this area, we do have
industrial uses.
With the BP zone, again,
yes, I know it is being proposed as data
center, but the BP zone does allow for a
variety of uses. When staff reviews
these zone districts,
we don't look at just the one use. We
have to account for that this could be
used for many more uses than just one.
But,
now I got to switch over to
the future land use map amendment.
Right now, with the future land use map,
uh this area is designated as
agricultural/rural
on the future land use map. Uh
basically, what that means is
back when the future land use map was
created.
At that time, staff didn't believe that
this area would ever develop outside of
city limits.
Um that's why anything that you see on a
future land use map that's agricultural
rural, it's somewhere where we didn't
believe residential was going to end up
developing,
industrial was going to end up
developing.
Um yes,
we've been hearing, well, why hasn't
this map been updated? We are working on
that update now.
Um things change over those years.
Um as I noted with talking with BOPU,
this area is actually developable.
Um they can bring utilities in and
service it.
With this future land use map amendment,
um
there's also the request to extend the
urban service boundary.
Uh we have done that with Bison Business
Park, so when that was annexed and also
that was actually that future land use
for Bison Business Park when it came in
was actually designated industrial.
Um not mixed use employment. Uh this
request is to mixed use employment,
which does support the BP zone, uh but
it also would need that urban service
boundary to be extended because now this
area is actually serviceable uh once
infrastructure is built and brought to
the area.
So, the applicant is also requesting
that uh the urban service boundary be
extended and then it basically the land
be changed to mixed use employment and
they're only requesting that for what
they plan to
uh what they're requesting for these
zoning map amendment to
BP as well.
Now, at Planning Commission, this is why
there is that overruling
um basically on the agenda.
At Planning Commission,
uh with the future land use map
amendment,
the vote was three to two.
Now, under Planning Commission bylaws,
that would be an approval.
Due to state statute,
that is not an approval.
State statute requires Planning
Commission, basically when it comes to
um
future land use map or plan updates,
basically. They have to have a majority
of the commission vote in favor.
So, they would have had to have four
members vote yes.
We did not have a full planning
commission that night. We had two
members absent, so there was no
basically would be challenging
uh to get that uh vote. We actually had
a tie on the item. That's why it's three
to two. Our chair actually had to vote,
but our chair can only vote
when there's a tie.
So, if we had enough planning commission
members, uh which there's a couple items
on the agenda where they have the
overruling, we actually had a lack of a
second
on one,
and then we actually had a two to three
on the other.
If the vote on this item actually was a
we'll just say
a one to three vote,
the chair would not have voted.
So, even per state statute when you need
a majority, due to bylaws, the chair can
only vote when there's a tie.
So, either way, you would not have the
four votes
um to have the recommendation of
approval
um with the future land use map
amendment yet.
Per bylaws, it would have had a
recommendation of approval.
So, that is why you have that
overruling. Um in the case of plans,
planning commission
basically approves or denies, but state
statute also gives the governing body
the ability to overrule that and
basically approve it should you choose.
So, there are those two items on the
agenda for the overruling, and then
the future land use map amendment.
Now, because planning commission
recommend basically didn't have the four
yes votes,
it basically came to the recommendation
of denial or failed to approve,
basically, for the future land use map
amendment. Because the future land use
map amendment failed,
They also then recommended a
denial of the zoning map amendment
because again
the future land use map amendment is
needed to get the mixed use employment
designation which then supports the
rezoning to business park.
Um
with the future land use map amendment
the business park
uh zoning isn't necessarily
uh
blanking on the word that I want to use
um supported by the future land use map
uh due to it being agricultural/rural.
So those are the
as five items on the agenda.
Um
staff
does recommend approval of the
annexation.
Staff would recommend approval of the
assigned zoning.
Um staff was recommending approval of
the zone change and recommending
approval of the future land use map
amendment.
Again, planning commission did not uh
recommend
or basically their due failed to have
four affirmative votes. There is that
recommend basically there is no approval
on the future land use map amendment.
And then a
recommendation of denial on the zone
change.
When we get to the future land use map
amendment
um
I'll bring this back up but staff is
actually going to
request those basically the
um
overrule and the future land use map
amendment actually be postponed
uh 2 weeks and the reason for that is so
they line up on third reading with all
the other items.
Now obviously if council ends up not
approving the annexation on second
reading, everything else will have to
fail as well. But if everything is
moving forward to third reading, we
would need to postpone the future land
use map amendment and the overruling so
that every item lines up on third
reading.
We cannot act on the future land use map
amendment until the land is annexed.
Uh the reason for that is that county
commissioners this then go to them for
concurrence or basically for a vote. It
went to them for comment only.
They made no comments. There was no
discussion from them. They had no
comments on it. It was presented to
them. Um
but they did not vote on it.
Because it's outside of city limits
currently,
we cannot act on that until it is
annexed. So, we would have to postpone
the item, but staff submitted this ahead
of time
so that we could have all of this
discussion at once, unlike what we did
with the Cox Ranch annexation.
So, we did learn from that that
we're going to have these discussions if
we have all this at once.
Um so, that's why we submitted it now,
but we would recommend postponement on
those.
Going back to the current item we were
on,
um just so
I can bring it back.
We are on the annexation, so we are
discussing
the land to be annexed.
Um
ultimately, annexation does not define
the use of the land.
Um
but again, with the annexation, it is
roughly 46% contiguous and utilities can
be extended to the area making it
serviceable.
With that, I am available for any
questions, whether chair, if you want
them to be specific to annexation or the
project as a whole, but I know we will
be going through each individual
item, so I'm more than happy to take
questions on whichever piece.
Um but again, we are on the annexation
for discussion.
>> Thank you, Mr. White. So, we are going
to be discussing uh only the annexation
of the um property at this point. Um so,
if you would like if you are here and
would like to make public comment, this
would be your opportunity to discuss the
annexation of those 3400
plus acres.
>> Madam Chair.
>> Yes.
>> I have a question, sure.
>> Go ahead. I'm sorry.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. So, through
you, I just want to be very clear, so
I'm understanding exactly what we're
doing here.
So, we're only talking about annexation.
We're not talking about data centers.
We're just talking about annexing the
land. Is that correct?
>> That is correct.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Madam Chair, just
so everyone is aware, yes, this is about
the annexation.
Through the zoning, when we get to BP
zoning or the future land use map,
I would say if that's the discussion
people want to have when it comes to
data centers, that is really what allows
the use are those two items.
Annexation does not allow the use.
>> Okay.
>> Um
I think it was even stated at one point,
if this doesn't get annexed, it could
develop as a data center in the county.
Um so, annexation does not define that
use. It is the zoning to BP and the
future land use map
that actually define what uses can go on
the land.
>> So, I have a follow-up.
>> You go ahead.
>> So, for follow-up, we will talk about
data centers in zoning.
>> Madam Chair, through you.
>> Just won't talk about data centers in
annexation.
>> Madam Chair, through you, that
that is how staff would look at it is
we're talking about the annexation of
30, almost 3500 acres of land.
Does it meet the state statute
requirements for annexation?
In two items, when we get to the BP
zoning,
that's when the use, basically, if
people want to discuss uses, that is
really the use discussion.
>> Okay, Dr. Evans.
>> And then, uh through you, Madam Chair,
my last question is this is an owner
requested annexation, correct?
>> Madam Chair, through you, yes.
>> Not city.
>> Correct. All 3500 acres are owner
requested, owner petitioned. The city
has no involvement
with annexing with petitioning.
>> Can you just um for the audience as well
as for our edification here, remind us
that the
um
annexation would then allow
the owner of this property to access uh
city water and sewer versus being on
wells or
uh having septic systems.
>> Yes, ma'am, chair, through you. Uh with
annexation, should the land be annexed,
uh basically they are required to hook
to city water and sewer.
Uh we don't allow septics within city
limits. Uh you can drill wells for
irrigation is my understanding, but not
for
uses of the land.
Um so, if this wasn't annexed, then
that's where you get into wells,
septics, all of that. But upon
annexation, they're basically required
to hook to city water and sewer.
>> Okay, thank you.
Okay, so we're going to take public
comment, and this will be simply on the
annexation. Um you we'll start the
3-minute clock. Um and then um we would
encourage you to um
be succinct and to use your 3 minutes
wisely. So, whoever would like to start.
>> Hi, Heather Madrid. Um
I'm going to stick to the annexation,
even though I find that a little silly.
Um I'm opposed to the annexation. Uh it
was mentioned at a previous meeting that
this is
changing the color on the map, which is
kind of
a bit of an understatement, to say the
least. Um this will forever commit the
city's resources to this massive parcel
of land and to a developer who has
admitted that they don't finalize plan.
Um Microsoft cannot tell this community
or the council how many buildings there
will be and therefore they cannot
predict water usage.
They cannot predict how the grid will be
impacted and how wildlife in the
ecosystem will be protected.
Without having a plan, it is impossible
to prove that this annexation is
protecting the health, safety, and
welfare of the community,
which is not a simple suggestion. It's
one of the criteria required by law when
considering annexation.
Last week, the city planners answered
yes to a checklist of questions about
the annexation indicating that they had
done their due diligence,
but then disclosed that they have hadn't
even met with Microsoft regarding the
project.
This project is at least a 10-year
build-out. Annexing this property on a
blank check with zero guarantees is very
fiscally irresponsible, among other
things.
It has been stated that Microsoft has
been a good community partner, but
corporate philanthropy does not excuse
them from following the same rules and
regulations as other companies.
It does not replace proper planning.
If the developer cannot provide concrete
numbers or even a good guess on
infrastructure strain, then they are not
ready to be annexed.
Um please recommend a no vote or at the
very least a postponement until a
complete plan is presented and the
required criteria has been met.
Also, congratulations, Mr. White. That
was incredible gymnastics. You should be
in the Olympics.
Okay.
Mr. Lyle.
>> My name is Richard Lyle. I live
in the
Western Hills area. I'm not affiliated
with Microsoft or any developer.
The way I understand it,
uh city of Cheyenne has a noise
ordinance
of limiting, I think, 60 decibels.
Now, if this
land is not an annexed and there's a
facility built on this exact site,
they could have noise of
100 or 200 decibels and this city
and this body could do nothing about it.
And so, it might be
within the criteria of the state to
allow regulation of noise.
Next, I'd like to mention the
aquifer.
The aquifer under
the in the unincorporated area is drying
up.
I have a friend who has
is out there.
He has a well that goes down 600 ft.
He has to now
because that's drying up
spend $120,000
for replace it with a well going down
900 ft.
Um
he doesn't think it's uh in the best
interest of anybody to drain the
aquifer.
Um
>> [snorts]
>> Now, ano- another change is
as I understand it there's going to be a
uh
if they build something there, there'll
be property tax.
And I don't know if they build
I I haven't been able to get the
calculations,
but a $100 million facility, for
instance, it could be that. I don't know
how they're going to assess it. Um I
assume that
uh homestead exemptions and veterans
exemptions will not apply to Microsoft.
Um
and how the property tax would be
uh divided up between different
districts.
But, if the property is not annexed,
there'll be exactly not one penny going
to the city of Cheyenne
of that property tax.
And I think it's in the best interest to
get a little more revenue in cuz I think
I can give you a list of potholes that
need to be filled. And
>> [laughter]
>> And
I think that would be in the best
interest of the people.
So, those are my three comments.
Um
If you're worried about the whole idea
of AI,
I would ask you to Google the story of
uh
Ned Ludd, L U D D, of Nottingham,
England.
>> Thank you.
Thank you, Mr. Lyle.
>> Yeah.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Hello, my name is Yana Ilyush, I'm a
homeowner here in Cheyenne. I am opposed
to annexation because
I do not trust any of you who voted
against the moratorium on data center to
look out for the well-being of the city
of Cheyenne.
And I will do whatever I can in the next
few months and couple of years to make
sure that everyone except for Mr. Moody,
who voted in favor of the moratorium, is
replaced. I also hope that I'll I'll do
whatever I can to make sure that our
county commissioners are replaced as
well because they don't seem to be
looking out for our well-being of the
people of Cheyenne. So, I don't trust
you with this decision. Based on how
everything went, I was here here on May
26th until almost midnight, and the way
you behaved and your comments, and I
sent you information through email, a
couple of emails to all of you, what you
said showed that you completely ignored
my information about instabilities in
the power grid that are
information that with very serious
references by scientists and by the
Department of Energy.
Um
And
the data centers
it it's a very large area, and I don't
believe for a second that these people
from Microsoft who are here are planning
to buy a home anywhere
next to the data centers they want to
build. Why don't we start at a smaller
scale? But like I said, I don't trust
you even annexing the smaller part
because
what you know how you behave and
the sound cannot be There's not going to
be so many buildings. They're not even
telling us how many.
This low frequency sound cannot be
stopped by any kind of shielding. Even
if it's reduced a little bit, it's a
humming that is literally like torture
to people. I'm telling people to drive
out on Happy Jack Road about 3 miles
west of I-25. There is already already a
data center there. And I have a friend
who lives a mile away and she hear
listens to that humming 24 hours a day.
She cannot get a good night's sleep. And
I seriously doubt that anybody wants to
buy a home there. And most people in
Cheyenne are going to end up in this
situation. We're going to be surrounded
around at least half of the
circumference where you already have
data centers. West of I-25, we have um
Project Jade on the south. It's not
within city limits, but it's going to be
very big and very close. And now with
Microsoft, we're going to have on the
southeast at least half of the
circumference. And this is going to be
Even if you didn't make any noise and
any other problems with energy or water,
just the sheer look like the physical
feel and appearance of these buildings
covered by metal roofs. These are
totally unfriendly to um
wildlife and
it's
it We're going to start It's anti-human.
Nobody is going to want to come to
Cheyenne or move to Cheyenne. And after
these are all built, the property values
are going to drop and we won't be able
to even move away. We'll be like a city
of data centers and that's all.
>> Thank you.
Any other public comment?
>> Madam Chair.
>> Yes.
>> Can I please ask to remind people we're
talking about annexation, not data
centers at this point. Thank you.
They're not.
Yes, ma'am.
>> My name is Diana Tolman. I reside in
Indian Hills.
Um, I was there with the planning
commission, which voted it down.
One of the reasons is
you're looking at a piece of property
that's 1/5 of Cheyenne.
1/5 of Cheyenne.
That is going to dramatically change
Cheyenne.
And I'm looking at this and this is
right now ranching property, you know,
part of it is ran- it's ranch
property and, you know, we host Cheyenne
Frontier Days.
That is a big money maker for us.
I'm looking at
if I was coming into Cheyenne,
well, you know, I didn't live here my
entire life. I grew up here and then
I've returned.
So, I've lived half of my life here. I'm
72 now, so it's a good chunk of of
my life.
And
Cheyenne Frontier Days has always been a
big thing.
But, are they going to want to come here
when like you said, you look at it and
it's all data centers and they're going,
"Where are the ranches? Where are the
cowboys?"
You know, people would ask me, they'd
say, "Where did you grow up?" I said,
"Cheyenne."
"Oh, do you own a ranch? Do you live on
a ranch?" And I had to say, "No, I live
in the city property."
But,
what are we going to say now?
Uh,
it's
industrial property now with uh Cheyenne
Frontier Days.
Just concerns I have is that also this
property that's going to be annexed,
it's
not too far from the community college
and will that deer deter people from
wanting to come and attend there also?
So, these are just some of the concerns
that I have. They say that there's
enough water,
you know, there's enough electricity.
Um but from what I read,
there's so many people that were
promised that and then it ends up that
they have outages and they have this and
that. And the other thing I'm asking is
now how much how much taxes
I mean, you're putting this into a
business. Now will this business be
paying
taxes on the property or will you be
giving them an exemption?
Because if you're giving them an
exemption of some sort,
then of what value
I mean, they're making
a phenomenal amount and how much of that
is really is it just going to be a
trickle
that's going to affect us?
Or are we in essence going to carry on a
bigger burden by suddenly
putting
at least 1/5 in this property
or annexing even more
by the time we get done,
Half of Cheyenne is going to be annexed
in and we're going to have to deal with
that.
>> Thank you.
Yes, ma'am.
>> My name is Donna Prosto and I'm against
the annex.
Um I was born and raised in Wyoming. I
hope it stays that way. I know it's
fighting a big beast, but unfortunately,
this year especially, we're kind of in a
drought and it's a big deal with
anything getting built. Um money buys
everything, but it doesn't buy our
water. Hopefully, it doesn't buy you
guys, but
I don't know. I'm just against the annex
and I hope you listen to everybody
that's speaking that from the community.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Madam Chairwoman, members of the
council, my name is Cindy DeLancey
and I am one of the owners. I'm a large
landowner in Platte and
some of our property is in Laramie
County as well as Albany County.
I am one of those ranchers that one of
the others
uh people were talking about.
And I just can't I didn't come today
with the intention of making comment on
this on this topic. But this narrative
about people saying we must keep lands
in agriculture. There's another side to
that.
And I wanted to share that side to that.
My family, we have our ranch for sale.
Agriculture is hard.
We can't get fertilizer.
Cattle prices are high, but so is
everything else.
When it takes $150,000
to to purchase a pickup truck to to uh
you know, haul our stock around.
When electricity, you know, is is is I'm
on the rural electricity. There's no
data centers, there's nothing like that
around where we ranch, but agriculture
is really hard. Everything is expensive.
And if a landowner chooses
to partner with a project, any project,
that is their choice. That's not the
role of the government to tell people
they can or they can't sell essentially
their business.
Private property rights used to matter
to us in this state.
We're not serfs. We're not bound to the
land like it's the 14th century.
If we feel as large landowners that we
need to make decisions for our
operations,
we should be able to do that. And this
misconception of annexation and data
centers being one in the same, you know,
that needs to be clarified on the record
as well.
You know, this is a legal process
bringing land in the county into the
city.
A project is a project. So, I just again
needed to put that on the record. But,
this concept of people won't come to
Cheyenne Frontier Days because they
don't see ranches, you know, as a rodeo
producer, as a livestock producer, as
someone that cares deeply about our land
and the character of our land and try to
be the best steward that we can be of
our land,
I just felt it was really important to
maybe tell the other side of the story
of agricultural lands right now. Thank
you.
>> Thank you.
Yes, sir.
>> Madam Chair,
committee.
Uh my name is Wayne Lax. I live out in
the county. It's L A X.
And I really, really want you to
think about the bigger picture of what's
going on for the city. Um I've spoken to
boards and state things where they look
at one thing and they go, "Yeah, that'll
be good." And then they look at another
thing and they go, "Yeah, that'll be
good."
And
they don't seem to grasp the bigger
picture of what's going to happen when
you consolidate or when you add up all
the things that you're approving one
after another after another.
Annex, annex, annex. So,
this thing's big. This is 3,500 acres.
Um I don't suspect the landowner is in
dire monetary need
uh in this particular case.
And I don't feel that this is some
urgent thing that you all need to do to
approve this annexation.
Um I think there's a I don't know, a lot
of buildings in the city
that could use some work. There's a lot
of different ways
the city can make money other than
annex, annex, annex. And then DCs, I
won't even say the words.
Um so, I really am speaking for a lot of
people that can't be here on 12:00 on a
Monday. I got friends, I got neighbors,
I got uh
people in the Cheyenne area land owners
coalition
that all want you to
vote this annexation down. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Mr. Wolfe.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman, uh members
of the committee. Um my name's Larry
Wolfe. I represent uh Ward 1 on the City
Council.
Um this is just the beginning of a
1-month conversation about this
extraordinary
uh process and um the annexation
and the zoning that will follow it. Um
and so I've put together some ideas I'd
like you to consider today. I sent them
to you by email. Um I have extra copies
here if you didn't uh print out the
email.
Um
but I've
I'll save the legal arguments for later
cuz I look at this both as a lawyer and
uh also as somebody who's uh involved in
the policy decision.
Um annexation is the battle.
Councilwoman Emmons, it's all one in the
same because as the Chairwoman
acknowledged, it's a commitment of
resources of the city.
It's the commitment of the water and
sewer resources. So, this is where we're
going to have a have a fight and a
discussion over this where the battle
should be fought.
And here's what I've urged you to do,
and I drafted three alternative motions.
Um the first one is to move to postpone
to give the mayor and his staff time to
negotiate an annexation/mutually
beneficial partnership agreement with
Microsoft.
I put in there December
figure out whatever date you want. Um,
you know, there is precedent for this.
Um, in the annexation agreement that was
entered into with the Sweetgrass
uh, developers, actually the same
family.
Um, so that would be motion number one.
Motion number two is to in fact
recognize what Microsoft is doing, which
is asking us to
look way into the future, 10, 15, 20
years, and make decisions today that in
fact we have no basis in fact to make.
As we've just heard
Mr. White say, things change. As we look
at the map, things change.
We don't know, and we shouldn't be
arrogant enough to think that we know
what this is going to look like 10 years
from now. We ought to defer to the city
council that's in
sitting in your chairs today, sitting in
your chairs 10 years from now to make
the annexation decision.
Finally, um
if we're um going to do
an annexation agreement
um
I've made some proposals on that.
Uh, with Microsoft, yes, they've been a
great community partner. I want to make
them a better one.
I want them to be
closer, more invested in this community.
I've suggested that we ask them to
contribute $50 million
for community improvements
over the next 5 years.
Uh, and for projects of this size, which
will be billions of dollars that is
probably
undershooting what we should be asking
for.
The final thing is you could do is just
recommit this to committee, postpone it,
let Plan Cheyenne, as we have heard, is
underway finish and then look at it in
several years.
I've lots more to say, my time's up and
I'll stop there. Thanks very much, Madam
Chairwoman.
>> That's okay. Go ahead, right here.
And just so just so you know, we're
talking about whether to bring this land
into Cheyenne to make it part of the
city. It's called annexation, okay?
>> My name is Nathan Marvin.
I'm a student a student. I go to Rossman
Elementary.
I'm going
to be in fourth grade.
I'm just a kid.
So, I don't know a lot.
But, I know
that birds
are scared of noisy noises.
I know
there
are a lot of birds. They're only
only
live here.
And
I know that
com-
companies
like
to make money,
not protect people or animals. I know
that
we have to
protect what we have
now. I think
to see the stars.
Big buildings come with lots of lights
that will make the
bird.
I like the birds. Big buildings come
with too much noise. Please protect the
future. I
This are first. Thank you.
>> Thank you so much, sir.
>> Madam Chairwoman, Mark Woody, Cheyenne
City Council, Ward 3.
I won't repeat everything everybody
said. I know we hear property rights,
but just remember
if anything's built there, it affects
other people's property rights. We have
to take that into consideration as well,
too. So, there's something to consider
with the annexation. Thank you.
>> Any other public comments here in the
room?
If not, I see that we have Charles
Miller online.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Okay.
Um
One moment, please.
>> Um Madam Chair, committee members, for
the record, Charles Miller.
I'm speaking to the annexation of this
land and I am entering a formal legal
objection to this governing body's
unlawful attempt to gag the public from
discussing the data centers driving it.
Defect one, the due process double
standard.
The June 8th transcript
proves you already combined these issues
when it benefited the developer.
>> Mr. Miller, today we are only right now
we are only discussing
so please limit your comments to that or
we'll need to
um move on.
>> Okay, maybe then you could explain why
um
that the uh
Microsoft's representative and Cheyenne
Leads were allowed to pitch
the data center
during annexation talks and then when
the public attempts to audit
the liabilities that the microphone gets
cut. Is Can you explain that?
>> I can explain that we allowed them in in
in order to be able to limit the amount
of time that this meeting is going to
run today
and rather than having them come up and
do that their comments at at every
single one of these pieces, we let them
do all of those comments at the
beginning and there will be a public
opportunity for you to discuss every
single item
on this agenda but right now we are only
discussing annexation.
>> Um okay, well, that that's that's super
interesting because
I I just want to um submit for the
record that this restriction constitutes
a fatal due process violation
uh because you have disparate treatment
and denial of pro- due process.
Um
you you
Uh I mean there there's just so much
here.
>> I Yeah, I'm not going to argue with you,
but um if we could let them give their
presentation on every single item, and
I'm sure that there would be some sort
of an objection you would find with that
as well.
>> Well, the inability Here's the inability
to satisfy stat- statutory burden of
proof. Under Wyoming statute 15-1-402,
this body is legally mandated to render
a positive finding of fact that the said
annexation is for the protection of the
health, safety, and welfare of the
community.
It is legally and logically impossible
to satisfy that statutory burden while
simultaneously pre- prohibiting the
public from providing testimony
regarding the aquifer depletion,
electrical grid strain, and
infrastructural demands that this
specific land conversion will
precipitate. Silencing public testimony
while accommodating the developer
renders this administrative record
critically deficient and highly
vulnerable to judicial reversal. I
formally advise a no vote on item 22,
yielding my time.
>> Thank you.
Any other com- public comments?
Okay, hearing none.
Um
I would entertain a motion so that we
can discuss this.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I move to approve on
second reading.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Dr. Emmons and a
second from Dr. Rinne
uh
for approval. Discussion?
>> Madam Chairwoman.
>> Dr. Rinne.
>> In regard to the annexation,
this is about personal property rights.
You have a long-time ranching family
that wants to
sell their property and
have it annexed into the city or in the
other order, have it annexed in the city
and then
have the ability to sell their property.
Um I find it interesting that this same
ranching family has sold off a portion
of their ranch
south of the college had it developed
into housing
and nobody came forward to say we need
to preserve the ranching or preserve
this ranch as agriculture.
So,
um
obviously
going back to what some people have said
in the audience, it's not about the
annexation. It is about a data center.
But it still comes down to it's a
private property right that they should
be able to do with what they wish with
their property.
Um
and to say that how when does it affect
that if their property rights overlap
onto someone else's property right and
that someone else that that should send
then have some say in the argument or in
the sale.
How far does that go?
I mean, at this point do I mean, to me
you can extend that I know it seems
ludicrous, but you can extend the
argument all the way down to say
a neighborhood should be able to have
some say over who you sell your home to
if you want to move. So,
Wyoming is a private property right
state, has been as long as I've lived
here and I think it will continue to do
so.
I think this family should have the
ability to do what they want. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Dr. Emmons.
>> Um thank you, ma'am chairman. I agree
with everything Dr. Ernie just said and
I know that um
it's difficult to not conflate the
issues together, but this is truly about
annexation. We have to take these things
one step at a time. It's a legal issue.
That's all there is to it.
And and as he said, it's a property
rights issue.
If somebody wants to sell their land and
I think Mr. Lancey especially put it
very eloquently.
If a rancher or a farmer wants to sell
their land, who are we to say no, you
can't sell it? That's not okay.
That's their land, they fought hard for
it. They want it's their land. We don't
get to say what they do with it.
So, for that reason, I will be voting
for this.
Any other discussion?
Councilman Leybourne.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman.
This is a very unique and
important issue
crystallized in this annexation action.
And uh I think it's only appropriate
that uh
I review some of the experiences I've
had in meetings I've attended,
contacts I've had with individuals, and
opinions they had about this matter.
We are talking about
something that has
international implications
and they're commonly discussed uh as
this process went along.
It uh is happening during a period of
time when this country's a war.
It's happening at a period of time when
there is great unrest.
And I
believe that it has been noted in this
discussion leading up to this annexation
action
that this is uh
the period of time that we're in.
It's also the period of time that we're
in where
various elements of uh business parks
uh
are very much front and center.
Uh
the business parks that have been
developed, including
uh data centers,
have really uh kept this community alive
and
thriving for the past 25 years.
So, that's a real strong argument to
make that uh
the business park is uh appropriate.
I think that when we look at this, we
have to understand that um
there's a factor here that's been
briefly mentioned, but
I believe is a controlling factor.
And that is the fact that these that
these property owners who are
incredibly distinguished members of our
community that have done
an awful lot for us,
developed a annexation agreement
for the Sweetgrass property
that was developed as housing and
business across the street from the
college, about across College Drive from
the college.
I haven't heard one word
of why we haven't considered
an annexation agreement
similar to that.
And I would urge my colleagues and
anyone else who's interested
to review that document because it is
extensively deals with all the issues
that are included in bringing um
major area into the city.
Um it's it's uh
very interesting.
Same
property owner,
same City of Cheyenne agreement,
but we're not hearing anything like
that.
Where are the roads going to go?
What are the arrangements that are going
to be made?
And as has been pointed out a few
minutes ago here that uh
we're making a decision that's going to
be
way off in the future.
I mean, it's very clear, and I think the
testimony we've heard here today, as
well as at other occasions,
has been that this is
not going to be a uh uh
immediate development because of the
size of it is uh really tells us it's
going to take a while and that's okay.
It was going to take a while.
What are the conditions that we need to
put on to
an annexation agreement so that well
understood
going into the future.
So,
I know we're going to get to the
questions of the planning commission
that I attended here
not too long ago for 5 hours.
Um
and when we get to that we can take a
look at why the planning commission
felt so strongly
that uh
there were questions here that they
didn't get answers to
and they wanted to. And I applaud the
planning commission for their efforts.
Um
I think we need to remember that just
like
we people up here on
sitting here on the dais
uh
we're generalists.
We're elected to uh
look at these issues and make our best
judgment.
And that best judgment's difficult to
make when you get into
the various factors that are at play
here
in the immediate vicinity of this
proposed annexation.
The Tallgrass power plant
is a mega power plant.
And it's being built for a purpose.
And that purpose is to provide power
for uh
people [clears throat] that bought or I
guess corporations that buy that power.
I'm not an expert on the grid.
I'd
really um
very curious how it
uh
is going to work
and how it's being developed.
But, I'll say this uh
this annexation is happening in the area
that has
very unique considerations.
Partly residential,
partly agricultural.
Some of it's in the county, some of it's
in the city.
Um we're now surrounding South Cheyenne.
The questions of uh
water sales.
You have
Cheyenne Board of Public Utilities and
the South Cheyenne Sewer and Water
District.
So, um and you have
as I'm sure we all have seen
uh if you're driving out South Greeley
Highway,
a lot of activity going on out in the
county that uh
has isn't directly involved in this
annexation, but
is nearby.
So,
I want to caution us that
we don't have to hurry with this.
We don't we need we need to really think
about this. And when I think about it,
I think about the conditions of
annexation that are called for
by law.
And they are include
the annexation of the areas for the
protection of the health, safety, and
welfare
of persons residing in the area in the
city and town.
Other people might interpret it one way.
I interpret that as being a broad call
to us
to really think about what we're doing
and the effect that it's going to have
on our city.
And I recognize the comments that were
just made that it's a property right for
the property owner
to ask to be annexed.
I suggest
it's a responsibility of this body
to determine if that annexation is in
the best interests of the health and
safety of the community.
I'd also point out that the urban
development of the area sought to be
annexed would constitute a natural
geographic
economical
and social part of the annexing city and
town.
People can interpret that. I think that
that's
what we do. We interpret the law in in
regard to this action.
So, whether we have a yay or nay in
regard to what this specific uh
consideration and
that's pretty broad, isn't it?
Economic.
I think we need to consider the
economics here.
And I just heard some very sensible uh
language proposed by my fellow
councilman from Ward 1
in regard to the economics of this
situation.
Because what we're dealing with
is unprecedented
and
almost unimaginable
corporate wealth.
And finally,
the area sought to be annexed is a
logical and feasible addition to the
annexing city and town.
I don't regard it as I don't regard this
as being logical.
And of course, anyone can use their
logic as they see fit.
But logic to me means you look at the
you evaluate the situation
broadly.
And when this annexation occurs, as has
been pointed out here, this is the
determining action.
And feasible
makes me recall and look at some of the
actions we had earlier today. We've had
growth
out to the south and to the west and in
the in the south. So,
feasibility to me means the roads,
the development,
and how it all fits together,
not not looking at it in isolation.
I believe it's our responsibility to
look at it
broadly. And I And again, I want to say
we've benefited.
There's a lot of good things that have
come and
uh there's a lot of uh things that are
going to be going to be coming,
but I think we have to be careful. We
have to look at it in the white
that
our governor [clears throat] suggests
in his recent uh
uh
I don't know.
>> Executive order.
Um
whereas Wyoming's local towns and city
councils
and county commissioners have the power
to protect community interests and
further mitigate siting and nuisance
issues that may arise from large
industrial development.
These are the reasons that I'm going to
be voting no today.
And it's uh
a choice that I think we have to
carefully consider and that we're going
to consider
as we look further into the whole matter
of the way that the planning commission
looked at this
and their recommendations to us and the
way that our process here works.
Um so
I just wanted to be clear as clear as I
could be that in this extremely
confusing and controversial
area
we we I have good reasons
under state law
to vote no.
But I hope that as we proceed here we
can work on some of these issues
together. I hope that we can come to
some kind of a
better understanding of the financial
responsibilities
as has been suggested. And above all
else, I want to point out
that that same that those same property
owners
on that same property
initiated
and acted on
an annexation agreement that spelled out
what was going to happen in that
annexation. That isn't that isn't
something we're trying to make up now.
That is exactly what the precedent is.
And I hope everyone takes a look at that
because as we probably all
have seen from time to time
that developments proceeding
uh there's
uh
really a benefit I believe. I think it
was
uh
I believe it was appropriate to do that.
So, I appreciate your time. I would say
that uh
this is a serious decision
of the probably the most serious
decision
I'll ever be involved in.
Uh and certainly this council.
Uh there are forces out there that are
really difficult for us to grasp, at
least me.
I mean, I got a cell phone.
I utilize all these
factors in my life.
And they're not going to go away and I'm
not going to give them up.
But what are the impacts?
And what do What does the future going
to hold for us? So again, I want to
recognize that uh
as far as uh
what's happened in the past, I believe
Microsoft has been uh
uh
a good corporate partner.
Um some of these things need to be
adjusted.
Our Our Our uh
the
business parks have been a great
advantage.
But I believe this is just too much.
And we And really needs more attention.
So,
thank you.
>> Uh
Excuse me.
Okay. Um any other discussion?
>> Madam Chair, one.
>> Yes, Dr. Rennie.
>> I
I appreciate my colleague from Ward 1's
comments. I do um
I guess I want to point out to people
that
Cheyenne is
growth we're kind of prevented from
growth to the west by the base unless we
annex it and we've talked about that for
years and
nothing's ever come of it. Um the county
has let ranchettes be built to the north
and to the east so we can no longer grow
in that direct
So honestly, the only direction we have
left to grow is to the south and
I know that because of all the growth to
the north and the east, the south has
kind of been ignored
for a long time. But
um Cheyenne is growing and that's really
the only direction we have left. So I
want people to understand when they say,
"Why are you
picking on us and why are we Why are you
coming this direction?"
We're really limited to the other in the
other directions. So it is somewhat of a
logical extension
of the city to grow to the south.
>> Okay, Dr. Emmons.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman. Um the
other thing I want to say is
what we've heard today is that we're not
listening. We haven't heard you. We're
not paying attention. This is probably
the seventh, eighth hour
that we've taken comments on both sides,
but that's the thing. They're on both
sides. This is not just a one-sided
issue.
I can show you just as many people who
have said they are supportive of
annexation and other projects as not.
So, please
recognize that not listening is not the
same as not agreeing.
We have to make some very difficult,
challenging decisions up here.
And just like the gentleman, somebody
said it's maybe it was um
Councilor Wolf, uh that it's a big
issue. It's a huge issue.
And we have tried diligently to listen
to both sides.
And there's it's much bigger than what
you're even hearing. I mean, when you
start layering all the pieces together,
it's very complex. But please keep in
mind that just because we may not agree
with you, doesn't mean we're not
listening.
That's a big difference.
So, thank you.
>> Any other comments or discussion from
the council?
The committee.
Okay, all in favor say I.
All opposed?
>> No.
>> Okay, we have Dr. Renny and Dr. Emmons
voting yes and Councilman Laybourne
voting no. Uh this will go forward with
recommendation to the council meeting on
Monday night. Um next item, which will
be just the zoning of going to
agriculture. Simply giving this land
a zone to match it up with the county's
land annexation, which is agriculture.
>> Jennifer, number 23 ordinance second
reading amending the official zoning map
of the city of Cheyenne establishing the
zoning classification of AG agricultural
for land annexed to the city of Cheyenne
locate located east of South Greeley
Highway and south of the Sweetgrass
subdivision.
>> Okay, and staff report, please.
>> Uh Madam Chair, members of the
uh committee
as a reminder, this is the assigned
zoning.
So, with any annexation, we do have to
give property a city zone.
Based on staff's review, we recommend
the AG zone based on the size and
current use.
Um that would give it its base zone so
that it has some sort of zone when it
gets annexed. Planning Commission did
recommend approval of the assigned
zoning to AG. And I do stand for any
questions.
>> Okay, thank you.
Um is there any question from the
committee for staff?
Okay, any public comment?
This is strictly on the zoning to AG or
agriculture.
>> Hi, Heather Madrone. I'm going to be
quick. Um I just think that it's really
hypocritical to say that
um just earlier today there was
conversation about what's already in
this area to include gravel pits
um an oil oil field and all kinds of
industrial. I've been out there multiple
times. It's it's in
industrial out there.
And to say that it's um agricultural
when it benefits
the agenda and then to say that it's
industrial
probably, I don't know,
two steps down the road is hypocritical
and it just feels like a manipulation of
the um intent for the land use and for
the zoning measures and things like
that. It just feels very dishonest to
me.
>> And I believe that you'll see it's the
very next item on the agenda where we'll
be talking about business park
zoning. So, it's just two separate
steps. But, thank you.
Any other comments?
Anyone online? Mr. Miller?
>> Can you hear me?
>> I can.
>> Okay. Madam Chair, committee members,
for the record, Charles Miller. My
comments are strictly germane to item
23, the resolution to overrule the
planning commission. Is that correct?
You're on 23?
>> No, they actually voted for this.
>> Oh, wait. Is this item 23?
>> This is item number 23, and they did
vote to uh zone this as agricultural
land if it was annexed.
>> Oh, [snorts] I'm sorry.
Uh one moment, please. Sorry.
Sorry about that.
>> That's okay. Getting the prompt correct
is very important with AI.
>> Well, certainly I imagine that you guys
are definitely involved
uh in in that kind of uh
pre- preparation as well.
Um
but uh let me see here. The
it this it's just a little
uh disconcerting when you guys have
>> [clears throat]
>> uh begun to reformat this entire uh
procedure here. Uh you allowed the
develop you allowed the applicant to
condense all of their
items, all of the different items, into
one speech, uh but now you're
uh separating the public comment on
that. And so, I I really truly think
that there's uh major issues um
with that, but
uh
let me see here.
>> Madam Chairman, I believe we are
following the agenda, correct?
>> We are following the agenda, that is
correct.
Go [snorts] ahead, Mr. Miller.
>> Um
I am entering a formal
Uh
okay, hold on here. I'm sorry. Can you
give me just one moment?
>> Sure.
>> Madam Chairman
>> Yes, sir.
>> This individual has
wasted a lot of our time.
>> Well, he still has a minute left, Mr.
Laybourn.
>> Um
>> [clears throat]
>> Well, I just want to know
>> Presenting Presenting unresolved
questions regarding
uh the
>> He He does right now, and then you can.
Councilman Laybourn, go ahead, Mr.
Laybourn.
>> Well, I don't know if you guys can
credit me a little bit of time there,
but
it seems to me that you cannot legally
bridge the analytical gap to assign
zoning when your own administrative
record confirms the infrastructure
required to support uh the applicant's
multi-billion dollar industrial campus
has not been engineered or defined. Um
to appro- prove this zoning assignment,
you must legally demonstrate that it
promotes the general welfare of
Cheyenne, yet this action paves the way
to eradicate thousands of acres of
potential residential land for
uh
um
who knows what? Right? Uh at the exact
moment this city is experiencing a
severe housing shortage. Um
It
It is a uh
It It is um a catastrophically and
legally indefensible contradiction for
this governing body uh to beg the
federal government for housing charity
with one hand while simultaneously
advancing zoning assignment designed to
wipe out over
>> Okay, Mr. Laybourn.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman.
Uh I think this is another demonstration
of how we need to make some changes here
in our uh
calls that we get from uh this
individual.
He repeatedly uh
demands
uh certain actions on our part.
He
frequently uh
alleges he has legal issues that are
going to be pursued
that are quite significant uh
they really confuse the entire matter.
Uh
Madam Chairman, this is inappropriate
process
and is totally unnecessary.
If Mr. Miller wanted to talk to us, he
can come down and do it.
And and this his confusion
his uh statements
uh really make very make no contribution
to the important decisions we're making
here and I think that
I certainly intend to uh
continue my discussion with the city
attorney's office. This individual
continually
alleges that we are breaking the law
and that we're going to have we're going
to be called into account for it. I
think that's the kind of
conversation that should never happen
and and would not happen, doesn't happen
with uh most of the people that come
here.
And so I just wanted to comment. I I'm
I'm believing this is poor process.
>> And your concern is duly noted.
Um we'll go back to the topic of the
official zoning map with a
classification of AG. Is there any other
public comment, Ms. Tolman?
>> Yes, Janet Tolman. Well, I just have a
concern because it's going to go from
agricultural and then it's going to be
voted into
um business park.
And I would just like
that the entire thing just be tabled for
a while
so that
all
all of these things can be taken into
consideration.
>> Okay, thank you, ma'am.
Any other public comment?
Okay, hearing none or seeing none, um
I would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I would move to
approve
>> on second reading.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Dr. Rennie and a
second from Dr. Immons to approve
um on this item.
Um any discussion?
>> Madam Chairwoman.
>> Yes, Dr. Rennie.
>> So, this just confirms our processes and
they they weren't meant to be
duplicatus. Um
we our process is that when
a parcel is annexed to the city,
it is given the closest city zone
to what its current use was in the
county and
um even though there is, you know,
a there's a gravel pit out there,
there's a
off Chuckanut Road, there's a
um solar field out there, it's still the
current use is agriculture, it's
pasture.
Um but ours is a two-part process, well,
three parts. One,
we annex and then we have to
have a zone when we annex. It just has
to be assigned a zone.
And again, our process is that it it's
assigned the closest county zone and
then,
which is the next item on the agenda, if
the landowner wants something different
than what's assigned, then they have to
go again through the process
and apply for that zone change. So,
um
this should be the least controversial
of all the of all the steps and then we
have to give it a zone and it does match
what the current use is. So,
I would assume we would have supported
the zone change.
>> Thank you, Dr. Rini. Any other comments
from the committee?
Okay, all in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
>> No.
>> Okay, this item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve at Monday
night's meeting. Uh next item, please.
>> Number 24, ordinance second reading.
Amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne changing the zoning
classification for land located east of
South Greeley Highway and south of Sweet
Grass subdivision from AG agricultural
to PUD planned unit development
I'm sorry, excuse me. And PUD planned
unit development to BP business park.
>> Okay. Um this is the a piece that would
change it to a business park um where a
data center would be allowed. So, if
you're wanting to make a comment about a
data center, this would be your
opportunity to do that.
Do we have any public comment?
>> Madam Chair, I don't know if you want me
to read anything.
>> can you Yes, quickly do your staff
report, sorry.
>> Um I'll be brief cuz I did go over it.
Um
so, again, the zone change it's for a
portion of the area to be annexed uh to
BP business park.
Um
again, that allows
a bunch of different uses. It is
adjacent to BP
as noted. There's other
uh
kind of industrial uses out in the area,
so the BP does fit the area. Um
this does change a portion of the Sweet
Grass PUD. I forgot to mention that
earlier. Um but as I'm kind of going
back through it, it's just a small
corner. It was not a corner that was
meant to be residential at all. It's up
on the bluff, so they weren't going to
propose that to be residential
up there.
But it is part of the PUD that would
come out. Um
with this, again, it's two parts. You do
have to think about the future land use
map amendment.
Should the future land use map amendment
not
be approved, then there would be the
recommendation from staff also for
denial on this. Planning Commission did
recommend denial, as I mentioned, but
that is due to not having enough
affirmative votes on the future land use
map amendment. The future land use map
amendment again was a three to two vote.
They did not have that fourth
affirmative vote for recommendation of
approval, and for that reason they
recommended denial
on the zone change.
Um
With that, I do stand for any questions.
>> Thank you. Uh Dr. Emmons?
>> No, I'm okay. Okay.
Okay. Any questions from committee?
Okay. We'll go ahead and we'll start
with you, sir.
>> Good afternoon. I'm uh I'm Scott
Bremmer. I grew up here in Cheyenne and
graduated from Central High.
After uh high school, I attended El Trip
for I went on to start my career as an
electrician here in Cheyenne.
Now 23 years strong, including the last
4 years working for Microsoft on data
center projects.
Over that time, I've worked on wide
range projects, commercial, industrial,
and everything in between.
But I can honestly say none of them
compare to the Microsoft data center
work we're doing today.
These Microsoft projects are on a
completely different level. The scale,
the complexity, and the expectations
push you to grow every day. For me,
personally, working on these data
centers have been an opportunity to
expand my knowledge, sharpen my skills,
and take on more responsibility. It's
not just about getting the job done
anymore, it's about doing it safely,
doing it right, and meeting the
world-class standards that Microsoft
expects.
Um but what stands out the most isn't
just
what these Microsoft data center
projects have done for my career, it's
what they've done for people around me
and this community.
In this trade, when work slows down
locally, electricians usually have one
option, we travel.
You do where you go where the work is,
you chase the money and you spend time
away from your family just to make a
good living.
That's just the reality of the industry.
What Microsoft has brought to Cheyenne
through these data centers is a real
change in that model. These projects
have created opportunity right here at
home. Electricians and many other trades
can make a strong, steady living working
on Microsoft data centers without
leaving town. They can take part in
high-level work while still going home
every night to be with their families.
And that matters. You're not just
building a career, you're building a
life here.
And the impact of Microsoft's presence
doesn't just stop at the job site. I
attend a lot of local events and
fundraisers in this community,
and at many of them you'll see Microsoft
or one of the other data center projects
stepping up as a sponsor or donor.
That kind of involvement shows that
Microsoft isn't just here to build
infrastructure, they're here to invest
in the community and support it. You see
the impact throughout the workforce and
local businesses and the events that
bring this community together.
There's also a real sense of pride that
comes with working on Microsoft data
centers. Cheyenne is now part of
something much bigger. These facilities
and critical infrastructure supporting
systems all over the world, and we're
building them right here at home.
At the end of the day, I've been proud
to work on a lot of projects over the
years, but working on Microsoft data
centers are different.
Because we're not just building data
centers, we're creating opportunity,
keeping families together, supporting
our community, and helping Cheyenne
continue to grow and thrive alongside
Microsoft's investments here.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Yes, ma'am.
Hi. Hi there. I'm short.
Um, me, too.
The struggle is real.
Um,
my name is Elizabeth Marvin. I live with
my husband and my two sons in the Willow
Pond neighborhood only technically just
outside of the jurisdiction of the city.
Um,
though I am absolutely still affected.
My husband is active duty Air Force, my
brothers are active duty Army, and my
father is a retired Army Chief Warrant
Officer who went on to work directly
with the city.
Except for the years that we moved
around with the military, I've spent my
entire life in Wyoming. So, you can
imagine how deeply ingrained pride of
place is in my life. You can imagine how
often our Sunday dinner conversation
turned toward legacy and what it takes
to serve your community.
Wyoming's legacy is filled with
industry.
Coal, copper, gold, timber, wind, gas,
agriculture, the railroad, uranium.
And with every new industry that has
been blown into our state, so have some
very hard-earned lessons. Lessons that
somewhere between our wind-swept
stubbornness and our cowboy pride, we've
forgotten.
Lesson one, newest doesn't always mean
best.
We all know the world-famous Wyoming
reluctance for change, but it's for a
reason. Our state is littered with ghost
towns built for proven industries.
56 that we know of. 56 where ambition
wasn't enough to maintain progress even
with out-of-state funding.
Lesson two, just because someone sells
you a gold mine doesn't mean you'll get
rich.
Carissa Mine in South Pass City never
paid for itself. Outside funding was
needed to open the mine. Half a dozen
owners squandered their fortunes and
legacies on something that never paid
off.
Lesson three, booms usually go bust.
Jeffrey City sprung up around uranium.
It only had 12 years of prosperous
future
before it was nearly totally abandoned
after the Three Mile Island and
Chernobyl disasters.
Those situations were out of the city's
control, but they harmed the people who
lived there in an unknowable number of
ways.
And now we're here,
once again talking about how to grow,
what the legacy is going to be,
what are we going to leave behind, how
are we going to affect the next
generations.
>> [clears throat]
>> Hoping
through these conversations that you as
our leaders
will
understand
where we are at.
Hoping that you'll hear us and you'll
understand that we don't dislike growth.
We want growth,
but we don't want to be sold out to mega
corporations. We don't want to lose the
Wyoming way. We don't want to lose
starry nights and birds from all over
the country.
Thank you.
>> Good afternoon.
My name is Micah Snyder. I'm a born and
raised Cheyenne, Wyomingite. I graduated
from Cheyenne East High School.
>> You may need to raise that microphone.
>> Sorry about that.
I graduated from Cheyenne East High
School and right out of high school I
joined the
Wyoming apprenticeship for electrical.
Um one of the first major jobs I was
ever involved on was uh Microsoft's West
Campus here in Cheyenne. So, I've had a
long career working on these projects.
Um most of my career was spent, however,
traveling
on the road and
seeking
uh
seeking work,
but however, today I'm back on a
Microsoft project working here in town.
And the thing I value the most about
this opportunity is that it allows me to
stay local,
happy to be home every night. My wife
really appreciates that.
And as a single income home household,
she's also still able to stay home and
raise our kids
on
this income from this opportunity. Thank
you.
>> Thank you.
Good afternoon.
>> Good afternoon.
Hi everyone. My name is David Zook um
and I really appreciate the chance to
speak with you today.
Um here is a Microsoft employee, but
more importantly as a Cheyenne resident
who's built a life, family, and a future
here.
I currently serve as an ITM.
Um in essence, it's a telecom
construction manager, but my journey
with Microsoft in Cheyenne started back
in 2013 with the very first data center
build.
I grew up on the East Coast and I'll be
honest, before accepting the job, I
couldn't have pointed to Cheyenne on a
map. But I took a chance, I drove west,
and it changed the entire trajectory of
my life.
Over the last 13 years, I've grown
through multiple roles and our
promotions within Microsoft. I love the
work I do and I want to highlight some
something people don't always see, the
human side of data centers.
Behind every new building, every
expansion, every project, there are
people like me whose lives and families
are shaped by the opportunities created
here.
When I moved to Cheyenne,
>> [clears throat]
>> and I just this heavy on me, I was a
single guy starting a new chapter. In
2016, I met my wife um and a year ago
yesterday, we welcomed our daughter into
the world.
>> [clears throat]
>> We bought our first home in 2018 here in
Cheyenne and this July, we'll be moving
into a new home with more space for our
growing family.
Cheyenne isn't just where I work, it's
where I've chosen to put down roots.
I really love it here. Um I've watched
Microsoft grow in this region and I'm
proud of the work we do.
Thank you.
Appreciate you.
Sorry, I'm a horrible public speaker and
I had to type all of this out, so I
apologize. I Put me in front of a
computer, I'm fine, but you know,
I've watched Microsoft grow in this
region and I'm proud of the work we do.
I know it can feel like data centers are
popping up quickly, but everyone
represents years of planning,
coordination, and teamwork. And each one
represents hundreds of people,
employees, contractors, and local
businesses whose livelihoods are
connected to these projects. I also
understand the council hears concerns
from citizens. That's part of healthy
community dialogue. But from my
perspective, Microsoft's presence has
brought growth, diversity, stability,
and opportunity to Cheyenne. It has
allowed people like me to build a life
here. It has brought families here. It
has kept talent here.
And it has helped Cheyenne become a
place where people from all backgrounds
can thrive. I'm grateful for the
opportunity Microsoft has given me, and
I'm grateful to call Cheyenne home.
Thank you for letting me share my story.
>> Thank you.
Yes, ma'am.
>> Hi there. My name is Amanda Augusta, and
I work for Microsoft. I've been part of
this community for more than 4 years,
and I actually live in town. I want to
share why I believe this is a positive
step for Cheyenne. So, in my role, I'm
able to tell and tell you all for a fact
every week our campus is host over to
host 267 full-time Microsoft employees.
We have 245 security and vendor critical
environment employees who show up every
day and dedicated to our sites alone.
And then we have 430 to 750 plus vendors
every week show up to our data centers
across Cheyenne alone. These are
long-term. These are not construction
jobs. These are just jobs that bring
steady economic activity into the city.
I can tell you for a fact the people who
work below me, 100 plus of our security
guards, all live in town.
Only two out of 130 or 40 live outside
of town, and one is in Laramie. So,
99% of Cheyenne resi- or Wyoming
residents.
Um another part um of my job or, you
know, we partnered with a local food
franchise company that last year. We've
actually brought their product into our
campuses. So, we're, you know, helping
drive that economic activity. I can tell
you for a fact, everyone was super
excited when they came into site because
we have fresh food options for everybody
to eat instead. On top of that, across
all the departments and the people you
see here,
those teams go out regularly to eat in
Cheyenne. They go out um and get takeout
from a Cheyenne
almost every day. There's something
going on, whether people are going out
in groups or people are getting takeout
ordered into our sites.
Um
beyond our day-to-day operations, we
like to invest in local talent. I have
personally um gone to Trades Exploration
Day for Microsoft over at Archer for the
past 2 years.
I've never seen kids more excited to
learn about different opportunities that
they can do and stay in Cheyenne, and
they don't have to leave. One of my
colleagues and I were having a
conversation because I am originally not
from here.
I was saying how I went to my my high
school reunion, and like 95% of the
people that I know live there still in
the tri-state area.
He said it's the exact opposite for him,
where 95% of his friends he grew up with
don't live in this area anymore, and
it's really sad.
Um
so, you know, we're able to show them
these great career paths that pay really
well.
Um that they can stay in our in Cheyenne
in in our data centers. Um this is what
brought me here. I have moved 13 times
in under 15 years. I have planted roots
here. I have told my husband we're never
moving again. We have built and we're
staying here because we love this
community. Um this is why I believe this
business uh park would not only be just
good for Microsoft, but for the
community. So, thank you.
>> Thank you.
Yes, sir.
>> My name's Don Taylor. Okay.
Folks, I'm a plumber, pipefitter,
steamfitter.
And I've been one for what, 48 years.
I've worked on two data centers. I was
at the thing at the city center
last Saturday. I left after half hour
being lied to.
I know BS when you put it in my lap.
And a lot of these folks here,
I've seen more integrity from used car
salesmen.
I've worked on two data centers. I know
what they're like.
I worked at Meta.
Probably the worst managed
job I've ever worked on. That's 48
years, folks.
I've been on some real messes.
Right now, I don't know but there's
activity going on throughout this
country
where people are getting up in arms
about data centers.
They're saying, "Put a break on them."
And I hope you folks start paying
attention because your jobs as city
councilman will hang on it.
People are getting ready to get
nationally involved like Erin
Brockovich. She's really tearing into
this stuff.
She got PG&E for a few million.
I hope you're going to You may see
yourself on Steve Bannon's war room
soon.
Folks, this is going to get nasty.
There are other means of making in
industry in Cheyenne.
How about
a natural gas plant for fired or a
coal-fired plant? The last one that I
worked on in Wheatland was built in
1978.
You put a scrubber on it, you can have
emissions that are cleaner
than you'd ever believe.
I worked on two
ships
that what they did was burn
basically PCBs nation-or Agent Orange.
And they couldn't get through the EPA.
Norway and Sweden were were doing it and
making millions.
The scrubbers made it so that the
emissions were cleaner than
they were 99.98%
pure.
So, coal-fired is should be something
that we should think instead of the
stinking turbines
that are all over our state.
These guys selling the flipping data
centers.
One of the numbers I heard
was 173.
That came from a one of our state reps.
25's too many.
The
you count them all metas one.
What What are you guys on to call meta
with all the plants, sir, one?
I'll close it at that.
>> Thank you, sir.
Heather.
>> Heather Madrid, um, Cheyenne resident. I
just want to start with saying that the
job of this committee and the council is
to represent the voters who hired you.
Um, all these multiple step processes,
it feels like, um,
the multi-billion dollar corporations
are being represented more.
Um, they have people here to represent
them. They're sitting over there. Um,
most often I see them sitting over there
with the people that are supposed to be
holding them accountable, laughing and
socializing.
Um, we're losing our voice, uh, because
many of our elected leaders have
forgotten who they're supposed to be
protecting.
They're supposed to be protecting us
from them, not the other way around.
Um, this final rezoning to a business
park, in my opinion, is the most
dangerous motion yet.
This grants Microsoft use by right, and
I understand that's not only in a
business park, but in this case
it is.
Um
this by doing that, it is the community
is being stripped of future conditional
use permits.
This is allowing Microsoft to bypass the
industrial siting council, which I know
that has been minimized, but it really
it's not it's not nothing.
Um for the next 10 years of build out,
this 10-plus years of build out, we the
citizens will have no legal avenue to
voice concerns over noise, water
consumption, grid strain, or other
public health and safety concerns,
because whatever they choose to do is
allowed by right at that point.
For some reason, it seems that Microsoft
has somehow earned this loophole because
they fund our schools and labor unions,
but targeted philanthropy is not a
substitute for public oversight.
Funding tech programs in our public
schools and community college serves to
train their future employees. Paying
labor unions for building data centers
does not benefit the community as a
whole.
Workers get paid or workers, like that's
not
some incredible feat.
Um
and that's nothing against the workers.
I want to be very clear about that.
Nothing against the workers.
Um
again, it doesn't benefit the community
as a whole. It doesn't pay for our
roads, it doesn't pay or protect our
water. It doesn't offset the fact that
they pay zero taxes on their servers,
which need to be replaced every few
years at minimum.
That is a lot of lost tax revenue
considering their business model is
thousands of square feet of servers.
So far, we have zero guarantees that
they will continue to be good neighbors.
We have We've asked for nothing in
return from them.
They should be paying They should be
paying for their own infrastructure.
They should be paying for their power.
They should be paying property taxes,
and we're supposed to be impressed that
our rates aren't going to increase
because of them. This is the absolute
bare minimum.
It is not a gift. Please do not trade
our communities a long-term public voice
for corporate handouts with a zero
guarantees. We need to demand more. They
can clearly afford it. We need something
ahead of time, not just relying on their
generosity and the goodness of their
hearts. Thank you.
Mr. White.
>> Thank you for letting me be up here
again. This time it's for the Sweetwater
subdivision and agriculture.
As, you know, we're having a meeting at
noon time here.
Uh, there's people that live in that
area that's south of the college drive.
There's a residential area, houses and
all that. How many of those people knows
what's going on right here now? Most of
them are working and so forth. Sometimes
they don't get the information. I don't
get the information for these meetings
or the count or county commissioners or
whatever because it's I have to find her
somebody has to tell me.
I don't have nothing against these folks
over here because they already have a
job with Microsoft.
I'm speaking for the future of this uh
data center Microsoft that is coming in
this town.
I like last meeting I heard one time
they're supposed to be they want 70 data
centers. How many do we need?
You know, that's my input.
You know, there's other things we could
do. If it was a manufacturing stuff and
so forth, that's different. Data center
is a whole different ballgame. It deals
with water, land, electricity, noise.
Like the G5 for example. Everybody
thinks it's not bothering? Oh, yes, it
bothers you. That G5's not uh good for
your health. People that live close to
it have issues. Trees are dying next to
G5. That's the example. They're that you
know, when you get something that big
as a corporate and their power,
we don't know what the source is going
to go in the future.
We have to be aware of what's coming.
Because, you know,
you know, later on
all of a sudden you find out what really
goes on and it's too late.
And that's just all I'm saying because
these folks that we're talking about in
that area don't even know we're having
this. I spoke I bet you cuz most of them
are working.
Need to have another meeting or
something so get these folks involved
because you guys are pushing this agenda
next to their area, you know, south of
Callister drive in that area
and they don't even know. So, that's all
I have to say.
Uh if you want to go ahead, these people
should know what you guys up to cuz I
know how most of them don't. They're
busy working like everybody else. I'm
just here because I retired
and I put 40 years on the railroad and
now what corporate is
all about. I worked and that I had to go
different places to work and so forth to
hold my job. I understand these guys.
That's the way job is sometimes.
You know, we're just
fighting well a lot of us are just
speaking up because this is too many
data centers or Microsoft. You know,
there's already some here. Yeah, but
these guys are working there. Yeah, but
the one that's coming in future
you know, we're kind of worried.
That's all I have to say. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Ms. Roster.
This is already
It's already green. So,
um I just want to say I respect Mr. Pete
for, you know, looking at everything
logically. Um how many jobs of these are
they going to be held long term even
after they're built? Trust me, I have
family members that work for them. I
have They're not happy with me, but I
don't care. Um I also have family
members that are digging wells deeper
because the water is just not there
either.
Um
as far as them working for these data
centers, they just pack up and move to
the next town. Um what's the rush on
That's a huge land of property. What
about the insurance coverage? Who's
covers that?
billion dollars of land or whatever that
after they're built. What about the
resources like the fire, police, the
hospital? They're already strained. We
wait hours just to get in if we have an
emergency.
And living here that's especially
difficult. I'm all about growth.
I just don't understand what the rush is
to just have it all bombarded into us.
Also, um
as far as like the city planning, will
they talk about that again or I mean,
obviously if there's concerns, there's
concerns with our resources. Um not just
what we hear screaming out of the
bathroom where I have to close the door
because you can hear them. I couldn't
hear you guys cuz people in the bathroom
screaming. I get it's a hot topic, but
these are the people in Cheyenne. We
live here. Um our bills are already
going up. It's I mean, we see it. We
don't have to look up AI. It's already
there. We feel it, so.
Please consider.
>> Thank you.
Ms. Holman.
>> Yes, I'm Janet Holman from Indian Hills.
Um
I'm an educator.
I spent many years um educating in the
school
district and in the classroom.
And
I agree. What is the rush? One of the
things that I guess I have a concern is
we talk so much about conserving our
land.
Um
China is putting their data centers in
the water.
They're not building them on land.
Um
You look at
um Norway and those places, they're
building them way north
where they're away from people.
And yet we're looking at building our
data centers right next to people
who have residential housing.
People who are settled here, here,
people who have jobs here.
People who are invested in this
community. People who are out there
working right now and can't be at this
meeting.
Um
and those are my concerns is just are we
going to say goodbye to the people who
have been living here for years and
years and years
because of the new opportunities that
are coming in
when we don't know exactly
how it's going to totally pan out.
My other concern is
just um our natural resources.
Um our
Has a study been done
to see what kind of animals and what
kind of plants
that we might be destroying?
Um
because once they're gone, they're gone.
You know, it's just not a matter of oh,
we'll just build it somewhere else.
We'll just
you know
take those animals somewhere else. We
can't if they're already gone.
So
I'm not against
data centers.
annexing property in
but I do have a concern for the rush.
I do have concern
because as an educator, I've got to look
at every single solitary aspect. I have
to look at the pros and cons when I
teach students.
And that's just what I'm asking of you
to look at the pros and cons before you
go ahead and just okay a project.
Um
and just okay an annexation
and just okay to change it to something
else.
Please look at
Please spend more time um looking
through these. Yes, I know these people
have been
you know, the people that own this
property now
have been and served our community in a
wonderful way. I grew up with Cynthia
Lummis. I graduated the same year she
did.
Um
but there are also others in the
community that
um
need to have their voice heard, too.
>> Thank you.
Good afternoon.
Hi, my name is Julia McHenry Robidoux.
I'm managing partner for McHenry
Holdings. We own property that is just
within a half mile north of this
proposed annex and rezoning. My question
is in reference to the zoning
specifically. Um on your maps you showed
there's approximately 3,500 acres that
is going to pose proposed to be annexed.
But then it also shows for this rezoning
the business park it's less than the
3,500 acres. Is that correct?
>> It's correct.
>> What portion of that 3,500 acres is for
the business park zoning?
>> We'll get you that answer.
>> While you're looking for the number of
acres that's going to be business park
zoning, why not all 3,500 and what if
the other remaining acres are going to
be zoned as opposed
opposed to this business park zoning?
>> Yeah, he's getting it he's trying to get
it. I'm sorry. Did you have any other
questions while he's looking that up?
>> Uh no, that's it.
>> Okay, more specifically.
>> Madam Chair,
Connor Way Planning and Development
Department.
So the total acreage to be rezoned
is 3,034.7
acres. Uh the remaining basically would
stay AG agricultural, uh which is that
assigned zone
um that
goes with the annexation. So,
anything that's not rezoned to BP would
just remain as AG agricultural uh within
city limits.
>> And Connor, you had said originally that
it was 3,459
acres. So, um
3,034.7
is going to be business park is being
proposed as business park. And then the
other
um 425
acres,
roughly, would be um set aside as
agriculture.
>> Madam Chair, through you, that is
correct.
>> Temporarily as agriculture, correct?
>> Uh Madam Chair, through you, uh my
understanding is there is a chunk of
that that is along the bluffs, and the
current property owner does not intend
to develop that whatsoever. They
actually plan to have a conservation
easement.
>> And that's
>> So, it would ultimately stay as
agricultural
probably indefinitely.
>> And staying in the Lummis
>> Correct.
>> ownership.
>> So, I guess I should say there's no
proposed changes to the AG zoning.
That's going to stay that staff is aware
of.
>> By the current owner, okay.
Um well, I guess then this jumps down to
the future land use
planning map.
>> I mean
>> Yeah, I want to come back to it.
>> Yeah, we'll take comments on that
separately.
>> Okay.
>> comments?
>> No, that's it. Thank you.
>> Okay, thank you.
Mr. Harwood.
>> Nervous here.
All right.
Uh hello. My name is Clayton Harwood
Wilmer. Uh I am a Cheyenne resident. Um
I have been here for over for my life.
Uh I went to Central High School, uh and
also attended LCCC.
Uh I have uh grown my career here in
Cheyenne.
Um so, with uh no data center
experience, uh I actually got hired on
back in 2016 uh as a data data center
technician out here.
Um I I then was able to move up the
roles uh into a senior data center
technician,
um and then today I serve as a data
center program manager.
Um I I want to talk about uh one of the
things that I just love most uh about
Microsoft, and that is the Microsoft
Give program.
Um and so, out at Microsoft,
volunteering uh isn't just encouraged,
um it it's it's part of the culture out
there.
Um so, I have personally been involved
in organizing and leading uh a lot of
these volunteer efforts that Microsoft
does uh in the Cheyenne community.
Um so, just going back just a couple
years, um from 2024
um through today, uh we've scheduled
over 50 volunteer events uh with local
nonprofits here.
Um and that does not include any uh
individual efforts, um you know, like
employees serving on nonprofit boards
here in the community, um because
Microsoft does uh donate when when
people serve and volunteer.
Um so, just some of these numbers, um
so, this is only from uh Microsoft
employees donating their money from
their paychecks,
uh as well as their volunteer time.
Uh cuz for every hour that a Microsoft
employee um donates their time at a
nonprofit, Microsoft will then uh donate
$25 to that nonprofit.
Um so, only from volunteer time and then
employee donations uh in 2024,
um it was just about $100,000 that went
back into the nonprofits in this
community.
Um in 2025, uh it was just under
$150,000
uh that went back to these nonprofits.
And so far in 2026, we're already over
$46,000 that have gone back
uh to these nonprofits as well. Um so
just in the last, you know, 2 and 1/2
years here,
um we're already over $300,000 that um
you know, these Microsoft employees have
given back to this community. Um and you
know, this is just all of us out there
wanting to do something good for our
community and and give back in the best
way that we can while Microsoft supports
us doing that.
Um and so, you know, I I live and I work
in this community. I am raising two kids
here.
Um so this isn't just, you know, a
corporation or a job to me, you know,
this this is personal.
Um and I I love the way that Microsoft
supports me to support the community.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Good afternoon.
>> Good afternoon. My name is Tommy Martin.
I live in Ward 2.
So I just wanted to briefly explain my
support of the business park zoning.
Uh so Wyoming commissioned Harvard to
conduct a four-year study spanning 2022
to this year to explain some of
Wyoming's long-standing issues including
and especially economically.
One of the key findings is that 2/3 of
Wyoming's students or sorry, of
Wyoming's born children born here leave
before age 30 and don't return, which is
highest rate in the country. And one of
the major reasons found for this exodus
is lack of career opportunity.
Uh cities don't get to decide between
growth and no growth. They get to decide
between growth and decline.
I grew up here in Cheyenne. I graduated
from East in 2008 and at the time many
of my peers believed that if they wanted
opportunity, they would have to leave
Wyoming to find it.
Many of us said we were leaving the
first chance that we got and that's
something that I want to prevent.
I don't I'm not here to tell a story,
but if I was going to tell you a story,
it'd be about a kid who graduated on
time only because he completed
last-minute supplemental online classes.
I'd tell you about a kid who had no
realistic way to afford college and no
clear plan of what came next. I'd tell
you about a kid who then joined the Air
Force as an aerial gunner and uh spent
five deployments in Afghanistan.
And I tell you about a kid who came home
after military service, once again had
no clear path. And eventually I tell you
about a kid who got hired as an
entry-level technician at Microsoft's
first Cheyenne data center nearly 10
years ago.
And I tell you about someone who then
worked his way through the organization
into an IT operations manager role.
But not here to tell that story. So, the
reason I'm here is to discuss the the
business park zoning.
Uh it's more than lines on a map. You're
discussing what kinds of opportunities
will exist in this community 10, 20, and
30 years from now.
I understand there's concern about
electricity, water, and environmental
impact. Those concerns are legitimate
and I share them. What I can tell you is
that very few organizations in the world
have the resources Microsoft does to
perform the level of feasibility
analysis that occurs before billions of
dollars are invested into long-term
infrastructure.
Reasonable people can disagree about
growth, development, and how to best
manage resources, but I think it's
important to recognize that projects of
this scale are not undertaken casually.
Even if you take the most pessimistic
possible position that data center
companies are only here for profits and
nothing else, a company is going to
invest that much into building these
facilities only for them to end up
inoperable in a few years due to lack of
resources.
There are very few places in Cheyenne
where people have an opportunity to make
six figures at a young age. That's how
you keep our kids in Cheyenne. That's
what my peers growing up here were
looking for when they talked about
leaving at the first opportunity they
could. Attainable, high-paying jobs
where hard work is rewarded. What I'd
like to end with is something that I
found kind of poetic that's happened
recently.
I recently moved from the West Campus
over to South Campus maybe a year or two
ago.
And now every day when I go to and from
work, I pass by my own stock old
stomping ground where I grew up, which
is AAA Trailer Park.
I drive past that trailer park uh
on my way to manage IT operations at one
of the world's largest and most
important technology companies.
A kid from Cheyenne, no technical
background, no college degree, right
here in Cheyenne, Wyoming. So, when
people ask me what the economic
opportunities like these can mean for
members of this community, I don't have
to speculate. Thanks.
>> Thank you so much.
Any other comments?
Yes, ma'am.
>> I'm Yana Ayash. Come on, I know
Cheyenne.
Um so this is about the zoning, right?
Okay.
So
first of all, about the I wish everybody
only the best, but um I don't think
giving people good jobs should be the
only criteria.
I grew up in Romania in Eastern Europe
during communist, and they were planning
all the jobs. Everybody had a job. It
wasn't necessarily good for them, or
they didn't necessarily do something
useful.
When I came to this country, um things
are a lot more complicated, and
governing is complicated in a free
country.
Um
and
it took me a couple of decades to even
hear about zoning. I didn't even know
about city councils for a long time, and
once I found out about that, I was
pretty impressed because I moved around
a lot around the country, and most
people are most places are pretty
comfortable to live.
But I haven't experienced any change of
this magnitude, and my problem with you,
all of you that voted in
against the moratorium, is that you are
not giving us enough information. That's
why you wanted the moratorium. You I
follow local news in social media and
the media, and there was very little
talk about the ones you already
approved. This is my problem.
You are try Why don't you put a
referendum here in November and find out
what everybody in Cheyenne cuz most
people in Cheyenne don't know
what you have approved so far and what's
coming here. This is totally
disingenuous. This is wrong for you to
do this, and I hope you're going to vote
for somebody else in a couple of years
or whenever you're up for election.
That's the problem. I mean, I understand
that we all have to agree. They can
build these data centers a couple about
20 miles out of city. The revenue
wouldn't come here, but it wouldn't
affect the health so much of the people
in the city. Most people drive cars.
They would be home in half an hour, they
could have jobs here. I mean, there are
other things there there's better
planning that can be done, but you
haven't tried to
tell people what's going on, let them
know what's coming to them, and you
haven't tried to do any reasonable
planning to make sure that we're
protecting from this possible negative
consequences. That's the problem. That's
why we don't trust you anymore, and I
hope you're going to change as soon as
possible, but
we're going to do I mean, I'm going to
do everything I can to make sure that
you don't vote, that you delay this
because we don't know enough, and it's
just wrong to push this down our
throats, and it's happening all
throughout the country. It's in secret.
Even if Okay, you're not like you're not
telling people, but you're not telling
people what they need to know to
understand this impact is way too huge.
The the surface of this is
I sent all of you emails about
um
the instabilities in the grid that can
happen because they have a lot more
power these new data centers, and this
kind of surface they're going to have to
Microsoft with so much power. They might
be unprecedented in the world. I'm not
only sure, but they have other big
areas with data centers, but have a lot
less power each. So, we don't know yet.
We have no idea about the consequences,
and you are not helping us at all to
understand what we're getting into. I
don't appreciate that.
Thank you.
>> Hi, Megan.
Um
I know that it's
This complication This This topic's
really complicated, and I feel like you
guys are getting yelled at a lot. Um
we don't
we don't we don't expect you guys to
know everything. There's you're not a
computer. There's no way for you guys to
know every piece of information.
And it's hard when people are throwing
facts and figures at you that you don't
necessarily have any experience with cuz
this is a big new problem. It's a big
new stupid problem,
but it's a problem that's here.
Um so,
if I'm allowed,
uh
I I I want to play just the audio of a
video
from a data center
of comparable size.
The video was taken less than It was up
on a bluff above this data center.
Okay? I think it's in Indiana.
Just the audio.
>> How do you know the comparable size?
>> Because it's got uh
it's it's got the
it's the proposed 3,500 acres or
whatever.
This is this is what you're asking us to
live next to.
With the lower tone frequencies
rumbling through every part of your
life.
This is worse than a refrigerator that's
broken.
The whole time.
It's why it's a big deal.
It's why it's a big deal. Our our
community is mostly elderly.
There's a lot of elderly people that
live specifically on the south side
because it's it is in the county, and
they don't have to follow a lot of the
rules
that the city does. It's just quiet.
Big noises like that with with
sub frequencies underneath them,
when you can feel the vibrations,
heart disease, stroke risk, all of it
goes up.
Kids can't concentrate. ADHD gets worse.
It's
and we don't expect you to know all of
it.
It's a big, multi-layered problem. But,
just because
70,000 people all want to be an
electrician and be paid six figures
doesn't mean that we give up the health
and safety of our kids.
We don't need that many electricians.
Why do we need that many electricians?
Why do we need that many technicians?
It's a It's a It's a failure in the
system to provide comparable
uh
salaries in other areas of industry.
But that doesn't mean that we need to
fill the hole with
this particular industry.
I appreciate your time.
>> Thank you.
>> Madam Chair, uh committee members, Tyler
Gibbs. I live in Ward 2. I've lived here
about 10 years.
Can't say I graduated from a Cheyenne
high school. I graduated from Buffalo
High School in northern Wyoming. I went
to school at the University of Wyoming
for undergrad and grad school.
I've been with Microsoft for uh about 3
years.
I can say from a grid disturbance
standpoint,
we don't disturb the grid. Uh if we did,
we would definitely get interrupted.
Black Hills would make us resolve the
issue.
Uh I can also say to national level that
we do have to work with NERC,
which is the Electricity Reliability
Council,
to provide our ride-through settings so
they understand how our systems are set
up and that we don't won't disturb the
grid.
So, I can speak to that. Uh the other
things I want to share, I do have uh two
kids, 1-year-old, 4-year-old daughter.
Been on the board at Meals on Wheels for
4 years or was on the board.
Now I'm on the board at the Cheyenne
Children's Museum.
I too love the uh
philanthropy that Microsoft supports.
Get $25 per hour donated for every hour
I spend in a board meeting
or any board activities.
Um
also, I've I've found it fun to
strategically try to invite some
colleagues
to come volunteer at the organizations
that I'm on the board at.
I've found a lot of success. One
gentleman by the name of Ryan Robinson,
he was donating his time every Friday.
And it was material and impactful to
the
um tour budget at Meals on Wheels at
that time.
Um
one other thing, I don't know if it's
mentioned or not, but Microsoft will
match
employee donations and volunteer hours
up to $15,000 per employee.
So, that can make a big difference to a
small community like this.
Last thing I want to share
in terms of new jobs and job
opportunities, um I do also work on
energy for our metro in Chicago and
Toronto.
I can say from an electricity standpoint
and ratepayer protection standpoint,
Wyoming's definitely set up better than
those other areas.
And I can also say
that I don't want to have to relocate to
one of those metros. I like it right
here in Wyoming. I've been here my whole
life.
And last but not least,
in terms of good paying jobs, I was just
able to post a new job opportunity here
specific to Cheyenne.
It's a six-figure job and I just posted
it on Friday.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> All right, um my name's Mark Mooney,
Cheyenne City Council, Ward 3. I won't
repeat everything everybody said.
We just want to think think about not
allowing this would not impact people
currently employed. We have to think
about that. It's not going to
only impact future potential future
employment. Again, we have to think
about those aspects.
When constituents talk to me, they
really have said we need to slow down.
That's from
you know, they're not here. A lot of
them are working. We have to look that
aspect there. We also need to look at
the land aspect. Big tech can't afford
to overpay for land when compared to
most other companies,
even some corporations.
Now, I've been asked to how come there
wasn't much protest with the gold mine
that's opening west of town.
Industrial siting committee, that's why.
And there was a lot of input there.
There was very low protest.
This kind of reminds me a little bit of
what William Jennings Bryan warned of in
the 1890s when you had the barons then.
Kind of seems the same here, so
I'll leave you with that. Thank you.
>> Any other public comment?
Okay, I believe we're ready for Mr.
Miller's.
Mr. Miller.
>> Hello.
>> Hi, can you hear us?
>> Oh, yes, yes, yes.
Okay.
Um
All right.
Uh Madam Chair, members of the
committee, this is item number 24, is
that correct?
>> That is correct.
>> Uh
for the administrative record, Charles
Miller. I'm speaking to item number 24.
The business park rezoning.
Um
I want to thank the chair for confirming
that the industrial data center use is
the germane topic for this record.
I'm entering a formal legal objection to
this rezoning based on the planning
commission's documented June 1st record,
which proves this committee is knowingly
overriding its own expert advisory board
without a factual basis.
The planning commission confession
defect one, in the June 1st transcript,
the planning commission did not just
disagree. They documented a specific
finding of fact that this industrial
expansion is incompatible with the
surrounding residential corridors. By
moving forward, this committee is not
updating a map. You are consciously
choosing to override your own board's
expert determination that this project
harms the general welfare.
Here's the second defect.
This is the loophole aggregation. During
the June 1st hearing, the applicant's
agent, Mark Christensen, confessed that
they are stringing together unrelated
parcels
uh solely to hit the threshold required
to unlock the business park
classification.
Uh this is not planning. It is
administrative gerrymandering.
Um now, hold on. Is this for the the
3,500 acres or the 320 acres? I'm sorry.
>> Uh this is for the 3,500 and I believe
the loophole aggregation was an argument
you used back on the 300. So, I think
you're on the wrong argument for the
wrong topic.
>> Oh, well, it seems to be that the
business park rezoning is pretty
uh
universal there for my argument, but uh
in terms of
the
3,500 acres here.
I'm sorry.
Uh
>> [snorts]
>> Uh Councilman Pete Leybourn stated on
this microphone that this governing body
has the clear statutory power to protect
community interests and further mitigate
siting and nuisance issues
arising from industrial development. The
hands-tied narrative used by proponents
is a legal fiction. Your own council
member has confirmed you have the
authority to stop this. A yes vote is
not an obligation. It is a willful
refusal to exercise the protective
powers you possess possess.
The chairs stated that this is the
moment to discuss data centers.
Um
>> And you're now out of time, Mr. Miller.
Thank you.
Okay, is there any other public comment?
Okay, hearing none, we'll come back to
the dais.
Um I would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairman, I move to approve on
second reading.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Dr. Emmons and a
second from Dr. Renny to approve. Any
discussion?
Yes, Dr. Emmons.
>> Um thank you, Madam Chairwoman. First, I
just want to make a couple of um
recognitions that this is not the last
time we will speak of this. There will
still be two more chances for people to
give their input in the evening, three
more.
Two more.
Two more. In the evening. Yes. So, after
6:00,
the first one will be next Tuesday
Monday.
>> 22nd.
>> The 22nd, and then 2 weeks after that.
So,
I want to make sure that that you
understand that there is other
opportunities.
And
that's all I can think of right now.
>> Madam Chair, just to be clear on the
record, just so that everybody knows, we
do have a fifth week in the month of
June, so we will have a week off, so uh
that will affect
>> So, it'll be the 2-week
>> June 22nd, and then it would be
>> It would be the second week of July.
>> it's July 6th.
>> July 6th would be the last final reading
of this.
>> And then I did want
>> Okay, go ahead, Dr. Emmons.
>> Sorry, thank you, Madam Chairwoman. Uh
Chairwoman, the other thing I want to
mention is that if somebody has told if
a legislator or anyone else has said
there's going to be 173 data centers,
they're lying.
Just flat lying. That is not a thing.
There's a lot of scare tactics, I think,
but that's not a thing. So, I did want
to make sure we're real clear about
that. You can have them call me. Yeah,
that'd be great. Thank you.
>> Hey, Dr. Renee, did you have a comment?
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman. Yeah, the
current census of data centers is
10 currently, five under construction,
and nine in the
discussion or planning phase.
So,
um my comments aren't going to surprise
anybody, Madam Chairwoman.
Obviously, I have been in I am in favor
of this all the years I've been in
Cheyenne, um
the mantra has been
we need economic development, and we
need economic diversification. We need
more jobs, and we need better-paying
jobs
so that our children and grandchildren
can stay here if they wish. And that's
generally what I have heard in the time
I've been on council and before I was on
council.
Um
so,
we now have an industry that generally
has very low impact.
Um we've addressed for the the power
demands, we've addressed
um
we've addressed the water demands, that
we have we do have enough water to help
to service them.
And so, we have an industry that is
providing well-paying jobs. It is
providing jobs not only to
at the white-collar level, but it's
apply it's applying jobs to the trades.
Um and these aren't temporary jobs. I
mean, if this is a 15-year build-out for
for Microsoft, then
that's a long, you know, medium-term job
that somebody can stick around here and
and make
make a good living.
Um
so,
we found an industry that will deliver
on what people have been asking for.
We've found an industry that turns out
to be a good corporate citizen.
It seems at this point to give back to
the community
um
and now we're being told, "No, let's put
on the brakes. Let's slow down. We don't
necessarily want those jobs."
So,
I have a hard time with that. And then
the other portion is
um as far as property taxes are cons-
cerned, Ms. Madrid was correct in that
the data centers do get a break
on the taxes on when they redo their
service, which has to be done about
every 3 years. However, I think that law
or that statute was originally put in to
give a break to the oil, gas, and coal
industries.
And data centers are just taking
advantage of something that has been in
place for a very long time.
They do pay property tax just like the
rest of us.
Um matter of fact, Microsoft is the
highest the largest um
property tax payer in the county at the
moment.
They also pay tax on
sales tax on electricity just like the
rest of us.
Um they pay the same water bills well,
yeah, they pay the same water bill the
rest of us.
Um they do negotiate they allowed by
state statute to negotiate a a separate
rate from from us
with with Black Hills. And again, I
think that large power user rate was
again put in place for our legacy
industries.
And it just happens that it applies to
data centers also.
Um
So, I
Oh, I also wanted to address the fact
that
um we have had data cen- as far as, you
know, it's been pointed out we need to
study the impacts. Well, we've had data
centers for the
longer, but the first Microsoft data
center was 2012. So, we've had them in
place for 14 years.
During those 14 years,
I haven't heard
of problems with livestock
animals, deer, antelope
dying, running off.
People haven't
shown up sick in extraordinary numbers.
The prairie hasn't been poisoned.
Um, so I don't So, I think from that
standpoint also, they've been actually
better neighbors than than some
industries we could have.
And then lastly, when people say, you
know, they're just popping up and you're
letting them come in with with
with no oversight. That's not entirely
accurate. The average when they discuss
when
when a data center contacts leads
they're immediately referred to Black
Hills Energy. Black Hills can spend up
to a year or two negotiating with them,
going through their power demands, and
making sure that Black Hills can meet
the power, requiring of them whatever,
whether it be a substation, new lines
requiring of that data center to do
whatever it takes so that they do not
have an impact on our power.
Um,
and the same same with the Board of
Public Utilities. If they solve the
power problem, then they have to go talk
to the Board of Public Utilities with
the water problem.
You know, we we've pointed out the
mayor's pointed out that um
currently our data centers use 93
million gallons of water a year.
And that sounds like a huge number until
you remember that when the refinery
converted to
to biofuels in 2020, we lost sales of
600 over
1.7 million gallons a day
was not being used anymore, which
equates to over 620 million gallons a
year.
Board of Public Utilities is selling 530
million gallons less than they once did.
Matter of fact, they're currently
selling the same amount of water they
sold in 2011.
Data centers haven't made up that use.
Yet their costs have gone up. That's why
our water rates have gone up. So,
when I look at at the overall picture,
Oh, one last thing. When this project
was first proposed to the Board of
Public Utilities, they told them no.
And finally, after negotiation,
and the reason they told them no was but
there was not enough return
in the way of fees on what the board's
investment would be to provide the
service to to all their buildings.
So, Microsoft has agreed to
and I I think the term is a contiguous
user in that
the board will deliver water
to Microsoft and then Microsoft takes
over the system after that. So, the
board is not going to be
losing money on the proposition.
Which that affects all of us.
Um so, when you look at the fact that
as Mr. Martin alluded to, 60% of of UW
graduates leave the state immediately.
75% leave the state within 5 years.
Um for
one
young person that leaves the state, two
people of my generations move into the
state.
I don't want to and I've going to knock
my generation. We generally don't
contribute a lot to the economy.
You know, we've bought everything. I've
bought all the tools I need.
I've, you know, bought all the furniture
I need. If I when I spend money or when
my generation spends money, it's
generally to go vacation somewhere else.
So, we need young people. As a
businessman, we need young people moving
in. We need young people making money.
We need young people that want to stay.
And so, we need these jobs. And so, for
all those reasons
you've heard me talk long enough. I'm
not going to recap it, but for all those
reasons I support this. Thank you.
>> Any other discussion
in the committee?
Any hearing or seeing none, all in favor
say I.
All opposed?
>> Oh oh.
>> Okay, we have a Dr. Emmons and Dr.
Rennie voting yes,
Mr. Laybourn voting no. This item will
go forward with a recommendation to of
to recommend approval at the next
council meeting.
We now come up on item number 25. This
item has um the entity requesting this
um change zoning map has asked for it to
be withdrawn. In our process and
policies and procedures we're not able
to do that withdraw, so we need to
actually um let this die for lack of a
second or vote it down. So that's what
you'll be seeing this afternoon.
Um so if we can have it read into the
record, Jennifer.
>> Number 25, ordinance second reading
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne changing the zoning
classification for land located between
I-80 and College Drive east of Southwest
Drive from MUB mixed-use business
emphasis to LI light industrial.
>> Okay, it's staff report.
>> Madam Chair, members of committee,
Conway Planning and Development
Department. Um as the chair mentioned,
staff did receive a email
which all of you should have that
basically requests uh this item be
withdrawn. Um to staff's understanding,
that's not council's usual process, so
staff would just ask that uh there be
the motion
to approve and then let it die for lack
of a second. Um
and then we basically can move on from
this item.
>> Okay, thank you.
Okay, um any questions from the
committee? Um
Dr. Rennie?
>> Madam Chairwoman, for the sake of
discussion, I would move to approve.
>> We need to go out for public comment.
Sorry.
Um, is there any public comment?
We're on item number 25.
I saw a John Doe with his hand raised,
but he does it down now.
Okay.
Um, seeing or hearing no public comment,
um,
I would entertain your motion now, Dr.
Rennie.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman. I would
move to approve on second reading for
the sake of discussion.
>> They will Do we have a motion to approve
on second reading?
Is there a second?
Hearing no second, this item will die
for lack of a second.
We're on now to item number 26.
>> Number 26, ordinance second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located south of
I-80, east of College Drive, from AG,
agricultural, to BP, business park.
>> Okay. Staff report, please.
>> I'm just pulling up one other thing.
All right.
Madam Chair, members of the committee,
Conor Way, Planning and Development
Department.
Uh,
this proposal is to rezone land near
College Drive and I-80 from agriculture,
uh, to BP, business park.
The applicant has indicated the request
is to allow a data center use, uh, but
other potential uses uses should also be
considered.
This is accompanied by a future land use
map amendment, which is later on the
agenda.
Uh, the recommendation
on the zone change is dependent on the
future land use map. Uh
should that item fail, the
recommendation would be to not approve
this item.
Um
chair and members of committee, I don't
know if you want me to also discuss the
future land use map or if we want to
keep that separate. Uh that's completely
up to you. They are similar
um items, kind of like the last set of
items where the future land use map
basically dictates the zoning.
>> What is What would be the committee's
pleasure?
To to have him do
your review now?
>> Mr. Miller might not like that.
>> That's too bad.
Okay, so if you'll go ahead and do the
overview now.
>> All right.
So
um basically with the zoning map
amendment, um
staff did review it and basically would
recommend approval should the uh future
land use map also be approved. Similar
situation that happened with the last
item.
Um planning commission did not have the
four affirmative votes with the future
land use map. That's why you have the
overruling along with the future land
use map amendment.
Uh in this case, uh the vote was two to
three, so the opposite of the last one.
Uh so they actually had just two people
vote yes and then the other three vote
no. The chair also voted in that
um that motion.
With the zoning map amendment,
um
again, because there was no affirmative
vote on the future land use map,
planning commission did not recommend
approval of the of uh the proposed
zoning map amendment.
With the future land use map
I will switch over to that.
Uh so, for the future land use map, uh
there is the again the resolution that
would overturn the planning commission's
denial, and then there is the future
land use map amendment itself on the
agenda.
Um
because this item is largely dependent
on how the committee views basically
future land use map, um
I'll go ahead and just kind of discuss
that cuz
that kind of dictates uh the path to go
with the zoning map amendment.
So, that item on the agenda is for the
future land use map is to change roughly
300 acres of land from a future land use
designation of urban residential, mixed
use residential, mixed use business, and
community business to a designation of
mixed use employment.
The parcel under the same ownership
already has roughly 87 uh acres
designated mixed use employment. The
applicant has indicated the request is
to allow data center uses, but other uh
potential uses should also be
considered.
The subject property uh is adjacent to
the future land use designations of
mixed use employment
to the north and west, urban residential
to the east and southeast, and mixed use
commercial to the southwest.
Surrounding zoning includes county uh
light industrial to the north and
northwest,
county land use to the east and planned
unit development to the south and
southwest. The PUDs do not allow
industrial uses,
but the LI uh would allow lighter
industrial uses, and the county LU would
allow lighter industrial uses by varying
levels of conditional use.
Current uh current surrounding uses
include mostly lighter industrial uses
and agricultural uses.
There is one home located to the
northwest. The future land use uh plan
did anticipate mixed-use employment
along college and on the north northern
portion of the subject property.
The size of the mixed-use employment
area was appropriate for average
industrial lots in 2014, but modern
industrial development has utilized much
larger parcels.
If the mixed-use employment were
expanded to modern lot sizes, it would
include most of the subject property.
But the re- uh but the request would
remove areas from anticipated
residential development at the time when
the city needs residential development.
The request also proposes changes to the
major street plan, removing the ex- uh
extension of East Allison Road, and
tying the extension of East Fox Farm
Road directly into the
uh extension of East College Drive.
After weighing the request, the planning
commission motion to approve failed by a
vote of two to three.
As the request failed to get four votes
necessary for approval, the resolution
uh for the overruling is required uh to
be passed in order to approve then the
resolution for the future land use map
amendment.
County commissioners will be provided
the opportunity to make formal comment
on the proposed amendment at their June
16th uh county commissioners meeting. As
all changes are within city limits,
county uh review will be for comment
only.
So again, with the future land use map,
it is changing
um
the area to basically go to fully to
mixed-use employment.
Uh should that have be approved, it
would support the rezoning of of entire
property to the business park zone
district.
Again, there is some industrial uses in
the area.
Um lands to the east are mainly in the
county, uh but our land use zone land
use
and would allow for industrial uses via
conditional use.
So, back on the zone change, again, the
future or the uh zoning map amendment
that is
uh under discussion
is to go from AG agricultural, which is
what the property currently is, to BP
business park. This entire property is
within city limits already. So, there is
no annexation involved. It's been in
city limits for
um a number of years. I believe this
came in with the annexation for
Sweetgrass.
Um
again
due to the
future land use map amendment not
receiving approval or recommendation or
yeah, approval from the planning
commission
they also ended up recommending denial
of the uh zoning map amendment due to
the failure for the future land use map
amendment.
Staff did recommend approval of both
these items. I am available for any
questions.
>> Thank you, sir.
Uh does the committee have any questions
for staff?
Dr. Rooney?
>> No, ma'am.
>> Okay, that's okay. Thank you. Okay,
public comment will open now. Mr.
Emmons.
>> Um Madam Chair,
uh committee members, Brad Emmons, AVI
agent for the
uh applicant and the owner, the owner
Reed Land Company, who is also on and I
believe he would like to speak today
on this and the applicant, which is
Microsoft. Uh Connor did uh that is true
the
uh when the Sweetgrass residential
development wanted to come forward to
get continuity with the city limits,
this parcel was agreed to be annexed and
uh be zoned AG as a holding zone. Um and
I think there was a question earlier why
some of this was done in certain bits
and pieces.
It's basically property taxes and fees
that are applied by the city. So
when you when you're going to bring this
in as
contiguity and you didn't want to pay
more property taxes, you leave it zoned
AG.
And so that keeps it in a different
level for that owner while they're
waiting to decide what they're going to
do with the property.
We have done a lot of great things in
Cheyenne over the 20 some years I've
been working on projects moving fees
later in the process.
I would say being able to do everything
up front is better than piecemealing it.
It allows for much better planning. But
as you can see with both this and the
Swan Ranch one to avoid property tax
fees and annexation fees and other fees.
In the past people would piecemeal
things so that they would only pay the
fees when they were ready to actually
develop.
Um
So for this project I would do a couple
other things.
This landowner has owned this property
quite a few years. I think at the public
planning commission meeting they said
they've had it for sale for 35 years.
They've been involved in all
facets of the Fox Farm Road corridor
study that we did with them. Um we've
looked at this property
developed in industrial lots. So at one
point there was a discussion of
expanding the Niobrara Energy Park which
is to the west which is small
industrial lots that did not work.
We've had
at AVI we have a apartment developer
that has apartments and
they were partnering with a residential
housing.
Um
that did not work. There was topography
issues and
for them high ground water for
residential. So
the ground water was not deep enough to
put in basements and the residential
contractor was not interested in moving
forward
without the basements on that side. So
um
That's the the different projects that
I've directly worked on this piece of
land. The other project was another
residential prominent residential
developer in Cheyenne who had it under
contract and they did not move forward,
but I do not know
their reasons. So, um
they've looked at the BP zone as this
has moved forward and uh due to the fact
that most uh part of the area was
already mixed-use employment, uh that's
the uh the zone we want to move forward
with.
Um I've also met with WDOT about the
realignment alignment of College Drive
and so Microsoft knows about all those
plans for the College Drive Lomas Drive
intersection as well. Happy to answer
any questions.
>> Thank you, sir.
Okay.
>> Good afternoon again, Chair, members of
the committee. For the record, my name
is Rachel Erwing, land development and
permitting program manager for Microsoft
in the Cheyenne region, and our address
is 1 Microsoft Way, Redmond, Washington.
Um I'll keep the READ item brief as much
of what I just shared for Highlands is
relevant and applies here as well. Um
however, this request is narrower and
focused on two actions, the Business
Park rezoning and a future land use map
amendment. I do want to note we also
have not yet acquired this property.
However, we are working towards closing
in the next few weeks.
Similar to Highlands, this is an early
stage land use request focused on
aligning the future land use map and
zoning designation so the property can
move forward under a clear and
consistent planning framework.
Where READ differs is scale. This is a
smaller, more targeted site being
brought forward at the same early stage
planning.
We believe this is the appropriate step
to ensure the property is aligned from a
planning and zoning standpoint. Thank
you for your time. I'd like to invite
our subject water expert uh to say a few
words as well. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Hello. Good afternoon again, Madam Chair
and members of the committee.
Again, for the record, my name is Dewey
Wynn, and I serve as the water and
wastewater program manager for Microsoft
in the Cheyenne region.
Our address is one Microsoft Way,
Redmond, Washington.
For this site,
uh it's a little bit different from the
Highland site in that water and
wastewater infrastructure does exist to
service Microsoft's proposed
development.
However,
utility relocations are required to
unencumber the property and make it uh
viable for data center development.
The water and wastewater infrastructure
relocation concepts have been developed
for the site in cooperation with the
Cheyenne Board of Public Utilities,
and the infrastructure will be relocated
uh in a way to enable both Microsoft's
development as well as enable continued
growth for the surrounding area.
As before, planning, detailed design,
and construction of the relocated
utilities will be 100% funded by
Microsoft,
and all planning, design, relocation of
the infrastructure will be performed in
direct collaboration with the Board of
Public Utilities and our local
development partners, such as LEADS and
ABI.
And with that, I'm available for
questions.
>> Thank you, sir.
Mr. Gibbs.
>> Good afternoon, Madam Chair and
committee members. Uh I won't bore you
with the power topic again. I think you
pretty well understand. Happy to answer
any additional questions if there are
any.
Uh similar to what Dewey shared on
water, there would be some existing
electrical infrastructure that would
need to be relocated. This is something
we have done previously with Black Hills
Energy, and I'm sure
we'll need to continue doing uh anytime
there is
an existing overhead or underground line
that needs to be relocated, it would be
relocated at 100% of the expense being
paid for by Microsoft.
Um
to Councilman Renny's point, there are
in-depth studies that take place, uh
transmission impact system studies that
take place uh with Black Hills. They are
lengthy.
Um and
they ensure that other uh customer space
retail commercial customers don't have
their service impacted by new loads that
Microsoft brings.
Uh similarly, uh as I mentioned uh
existing LPCS large power contract
service tariff that Black Hills has in
place
will protect other ratepayers from
seeing increased costs.
Uh available for any questions.
>> Thank you.
>> Good afternoon.
>> Good afternoon, Madam Chairman
and members of the committee. My name is
Adonis Trujeau and I'm with the
Microsoft data center community affairs
team.
I've had the honor of supporting the
Cheyenne community
for the last 3 years.
Now, I'm partnering closely with Lucas
Downey,
our new community affairs manager for
the region, and looking forward to serve
this community even more.
It's my pleasure to take a few minutes
today to provide an overview
and expand on the strong partnership
that Microsoft has with Laramie County
Community College, specifically through
a program that we call the Microsoft
Data Center Academy.
The program is built on five core
pillars:
curriculum,
a state-of-the-art data center
environment on site,
hands-on work experience,
scholarship opportunities, and
mentorship and support throughout the
program.
This program prepares our local
workforce for the high-demand jobs of
the future,
especially in IT,
cloud computing,
and infrastructure management, not just
for Microsoft,
but for any data center operator in the
community. And that could be
with any organization that has IT
infrastructure like schools, banks,
hospitals, nonprofits, and so on.
If we look specifically at the impacts
with Laramie County Community College,
Laramie County Community College,
we've had just under 1,400 students go
through the program.
Not just students from Cheyenne, but
from students from all across Wyoming.
218 of those students have received
scholarships from Microsoft to ensure
that there are no barriers to entry for
the program.
And since 2023,
we've taken in 13 interns directly and
have already hired dozens more from this
channel.
And we're proud of these milestones and
really looking forward to seeing that
number grow in the years ahead.
We want to express deep gratitude for
the partnership that we have with LCCC.
We're mindful of the proposed project
near the school.
And we look forward
to continue working closely with
stakeholders from across LCCC,
supporting this partnership alongside
many other initiatives that we have with
the school,
to ensure a deepened conversation and
sense of trust with the school and the
surrounding community.
Thank you so much for your time today
and I stand for questions.
>> Thank you.
Ms. Madrid.
>> Hi.
Heather Madrid. Um
I'm having a hard time at this point
keeping everything straight. Um
I
I appreciate actually Mr.
sharing all the efforts that have been
made already with this property. I think
it's really helpful to know that
there was, you know, potential for it to
become residential. I appreciate knowing
that.
Um
and
my concern with
continuing to amend
the land use
map is that
the intent is that it is a
well-thought-out
plan for development and it's supposed
to involve public input. The land use
map itself is supposed to involve public
input, not just this process.
Um
and amending it to continually amending
it to accommodate Microsoft and other
corporations
um
seems like a workaround of the purpose
of the map.
If it can be changed so easily on such a
massive scale, again, not necessarily is
perfect, but just historically, that's
what's been happening recently.
Um then it seems like it is serving the
highest bidder, not necessarily the
community as a whole.
Um and again, my my further concern is
somebody mentioned a minute ago that
this is going to just facilitate further
expansion and I just wonder, is
Microsoft going to own Cheyenne?
Um and it was mentioned that they will
own the infrastructure for the water on
one of these properties, which kind of
scares me a little.
Um if Microsoft is controlling our
infrastructure and our resources, um
again, I don't think that anybody in
this room is is less than trustworthy. I
just worry about really any giant
corporate global conglomeration
um owning us.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Any other public comments? I see Mr.
Reed has his hand up.
Mr. Reed, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Thank you.
Uh this has been a long meeting, so I'll
be brief.
Uh this property has been in the Reed
family for three generations now,
ownership of which was transferred to my
generation a few years after the
untimely death of my father in an
aviation accident.
While portions of the property are
designated for residential use in the
comprehensive plan, after decades of
marketing this property, the Reed
families learned that the property is
not feasible for residential
development.
Multiple developers have determined that
topography and other characteristics
make residential development
impractical.
Dating back to the 1990s, residential
developers have inquired about the
property, but ultimately were never able
to determine residential development is
feasible.
We were told by local real estate agents
that annexation in 2016
would open the door to residential
development, but that still didn't help.
In early in the early 2020s, the
property was under contract two times
as uh Mr. Hammond said, with different
residential developers, both of whom
eventually backed out of the contract
due uh during due diligence periods.
All contracts and interest in recent
history have been in industrial in
nature.
We now understand that high up-front
costs due to the topography and utility
relocation make the land unsuitable for
residential development.
Over a period of nearly five decades
now, the Reed family has made a solid,
good-faith, if futile, effort to sell
this property for residential
development.
The simple fact that no matter how much
the city needs housing, this property
has proven unfeasible for residential
development.
Finally, let me observe that among the
nearly dozen
negotiations for the sale of part or all
of the Reed family land,
those with Microsoft's people
have been the most professional,
the least adversarial,
and in most regards the easiest of all,
suggesting to me that they will be a
uh conscientious
and
civically committed member of the
Cheyenne business community.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
Is there any other public comment um in
the room or online?
Mr. Charles uh Mr. Charles, Mr. Miller.
>> Can you hear me?
>> I can.
>> All right.
I'm sorry, I just have to gather my
notes here.
One moment.
>> And we are on item number 26 if that
helps.
>> Uh yep, and this is uh PUDC 26121.
>> Sure.
>> Okay.
Let's see here.
Um members of the city of of the uh
committee, Charles Miller for the
record.
The Reed land rezoning
and the associated resolution, well I
guess this is just the rezoning. Um
First, you were attempting to
legally launder a
uh dead zoning request.
The foundational future land use map
amendment for this project
mathematically failed to pass the
planning commission because it failed,
your own planning department explicitly
stated on the record staff recommends
denial of the zone change.
Um now you are utilizing a procedural
loophole to overrule your own
engineering and planning experts simply
to subsidize a hyperscale corporate
developer.
Second, you cannot legally reach a
positive finding of fact when your own
planners have documented that this
action actively harms the public. Page
five of the city staff report for this
property contains a stunning legal
admission.
It states verbatim that due to
Cheyenne's documented housing crisis
taking this residential land and zoning
it industrial quote would adversely
affect the public health, safety, or
general welfare.
Um let that sink in. Your own officials
put in writing that rezoning these 387
acres for a Microsoft data center
damages the general welfare of Cheyenne.
Third, the applicant formally admitted
on the record that they are land
banking. You are amputating the city's
master planned transportation network
specifically deleting
the Allison Road and Fox Farm extensions
just so a trillion-dollar corporation
can hoard vacant land for the next 15 to
20 years.
You're stripping 400 acres of housing
from a starving market. You're ignoring
your own staff's recommendation of
denial and you're outsourcing noise and
environmental enforcement to private
anonymous LLCs that you have zero
statutory authority to regulate.
This process is legally defective. It is
procedurally fraudulent and I urge an
immediate motion to deny this rezoning
rezoning.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller. Is there any
other public comment?
Stolmen?
>> Uh yes. Um
once again, they said that they would
answer any questions in regard to water.
I I think just talking to constituents
within the community because we are
right now going through a drought, a
serious drought. We're always in a
drought. Cheyenne
and we're always in lack of water.
And anyway, that's what we're told, and
we're
you know, confined to certain amounts of
water that we're supposed to use.
And yet, a data center is being
posed to come into a community
that has very little water.
Now, the Board of Public Utilities and
others, as they have said, said that we
have plenty of water.
Um
my concern is just like looking at even
the southern states. Hoover Dam now is
looking at possibly shutting down after
90 years
of being in of operation due to shortage
of water.
And
we are looking,
you know, at a shortage, too. And just
looking towards the future,
um
I know that our community has just a lot
of concerns and a lot of fears about the
possibility of having no water and
becoming a ghost town.
So,
any
um exclamation, any information that can
be given, that can be passed down to
constituents to
take away some of the fears that they
have would be greatly appreciated.
>> Thank you.
Any other public comment?
Okay, hearing or seeing none, I would
entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chair
Madam Chairwoman, I move to approve on
second reading.
>> Second.
>> Okay, we have a motion from Dr. Emmons,
a second from Dr. Renny.
Um
is there any discussion?
Hearing none, all in favor say I.
>> I.
>> All opposed?
Okay, this item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve at Monday's
meeting.
Uh, the next item.
>> [clears throat]
>> Number 33, resolution authorizing the
mayor and city clerk to sign a final
plat for Harmony Valley 24th filing,
City of Cheyenne, Laramie County,
Wyoming, located north of West College
Drive and east of Parsley Boulevard.
>> Thank you. Staff report.
>> Chair, members of the board, Marie Coble
Nickie,
Cheyenne City Planning and Development
Department. This is for an expedited
plat for 6 and 1/2 acres of land located
east of South Parsley Boulevard and
north of West College Drive.
The lot is currently vacant. The purpose
of this plat is to create a common lot
and five individual lots for the
buildings.
Responsibility of maintenance for the
common lot will be split into 1/5
interest for each building owner.
They will be responsible for maintaining
the common lot to the approved site
plan. This parcel has undergone the site
plan process and received approval.
The future land use map designates this
area as mixed-use commercial.
This parcel has recently undergone a
zoning change from Harmony Valley PUD to
NR3.
All multi-dwelling building lot types
are allowed within the NR3 zone.
The lots proposed are reflective of
buildings on an approved site plan and
are buildable in the NR3 zone.
Planning Commission heard this at the
June 1st meeting and recommends
approval.
>> Thank you.
Okay, is there any Are there any
questions from committee?
>> Can we have a developer's report?
>> Sure.
He sat this long, he might as well talk
to us.
>> I I that Mr. Sayers has just been
waiting to get to this one.
>> Madam Chair, through you, I'm not here
to talk about data center on this one,
so you can leave all the friends over
there. Well, let's get through this.
Um we have an approved site plan through
uh
planning and through engineering for the
524s that you see on that plan. Uh the
idea is is that we wanted to go ahead
and do an individual building around
each area lot around each individual
building with the common areas, so they
they would have a 1/5, so that way taxes
and everything would be associated with
a shared group on that at that point.
I'm here to answer any questions.
>> Are there any questions from committee?
Okay.
And uh is there any public comment?
I see Mr. Miller has his hand raised.
>> Hello, can you hear me?
>> I can.
>> This is item number 33, is that correct?
>> Uh that is correct.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
uh for the record, Charles Miller
speaking on item 33, the final plat for
the Harmony Valley 24th
filing.
Um
On June 1st, during the planning
commission hearing for this exact plat,
area residents explicitly warned the
city that adding high-density
residential units here creates a severe
safety hazard.
They placed on the record that there are
no sidewalks on College Drive to protect
children
walking to school in a 50 mph zone.
When confronted with this life safety
hazard, the developer's agent, John
Sayers of True Grit, explicitly washed
his hands of the problem on the live
microphone. He stated verbatim that the
lack of sidewalks is  a city
question and is outside our spectrum and
scope.
This is the definition of privatizing
profits while socializing liabilities.
You are rubber stamping a developer's
high-density plat for profit while
explicitly allowing them to evade the
cost of the pedestrian infrastructure
required to keep their own residents
safe. You are dumping that liability
directly onto the Cheyenne taxpayer.
Furthermore, this plat establishes a
convoluted common lot maintenance scheme
split five ways. Your own planning staff
admitted on June 1st that when this
inevitably fails, the city will have to
burn administrative resources to abate
the weeds, mow the grass, and place
liens on the properties. Approving a
final plat that deliberately omits
critical life safety infrastructure
because the developer refuses to pay for
it is a direct abdication of the general
welfare. You must recommit this plat and
withhold final approval until the
developer is legally bound to fund and
construct the necessary sidewalks. I
yield my time.
>> Thank you. Any other public comment?
Okay, seeing or hearing none, I would
entertain a motion, please.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I would move to
adopt.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion to adopt and a second
from Dr. Rennie, second from Dr. Immens.
Is there any discussion?
Hearing none, all in favor say I.
Okay, this item will move forward with a
recommendation to uh approve at the next
meeting of the council.
Um next item is 34 and this is the
future land use map conversation.
>> Number 34, resolution overruling the
planning commission's disapproval of an
amendment to the future land use map of
plan Cheyenne, changing the land use
designation from agricultural rule and
urban residential to mixed use
employment, and amending the urban
service boundary for property generally
located east of South Greeley Highway
and south of the Sweetgrass Subdivision.
Okay, staff report.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
um as a reminder, so with this
resolution, this is basically what needs
to be approved
in order to
basically approve the next item.
Um
so, this is overruling the planning
commission's
uh
denial ultimately. Again, the vote was
three to two. Uh they did not have all
members present, so I don't know how
that vote would have went if all members
were present.
But, because they didn't have the four
affirmative votes,
ultimately, from state statute, it
became a uh denial of the future land
use map amendment.
We did have this once before on
council's agenda.
Um
so, this is the direction that the
attorney's office had
uh directed staff to bring this forward.
So, this is the overruling.
Uh this isn't necessarily the future
land use map amendment itself. So, you
would have to approve this
to then approve the next item.
Uh as I mentioned earlier, because this
is
uh all other items for the Highlands
property are on second reading,
staff would recommend that this item be
postponed for 2 weeks, so that it will
line up with third reading.
Um
with that, I am available for any
questions.
>> Um
Councilman Laybourn.
Sorry.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Chairwoman,
um
Mr. White,
could you run by again the difference
between state statute and planning
commission bylaws that seems to be in
effect here?
>> Madam Chair, through you. So, state
statute ultimately for any amendment to
a plan requires four affirmative votes
from
a majority Basically, it's
the way it reads is that you need to
have a majority of the commission vote
in favor.
Uh so, for planning commission, there's
seven members, you would need to have
four affirmative votes.
Bylaws for planning commission, you only
have to have a majority of those
present. Um,
and the chair is also not allowed to
vote unless there is a tie per bylaws.
So at planning commission, we had five
members present, two were absent. Um,
there was a tie, so the chair did get to
vote. Uh, but it did not basically win
with a three to two vote, which would be
an approval per bylaws because it didn't
meet the state statute approval of
having four affirmative,
it comes forward as basically a denial.
>> Thank you.
>> Um, chair.
>> Councilman Laybourn.
>> Um, this seems to be kind of unusual.
Um,
how often has that happened in the past?
>> Madam Chair, through you, we have only
had this happen one other time, and that
was the first time we had a overruling
come before you.
Um, but that was another meeting where
not all members were present.
Uh, and actually the chair didn't get to
vote. We didn't have a tie at that
meeting. Um, if you remember, it is the
property that was on Southwest Drive. It
was from Mr. Sayers. It was at the north
end of Southwest Drive that had an
overruling for a future land use map
amendment.
That's the only other time that I've
experienced it while working for the
city, and I'm going on 7 years here.
Um, so in my roughly 6 and 1/2, I've
never had a state statute conflict. We
also haven't had as many future land use
map amendments
uh, come forward.
But,
that is from what staff has looked at,
that is the only time that we can find
where state statute and the bylaws
are different. Um, which I believe the
attorney's office would like us to look
into and possibly fix the bylaws a
little bit when it comes to situations
like this.
Um, because again, when it gets down to
where state statute asks or basically
requires a majority of the commission,
but then the chair can't
even vote unless there's a tie.
I mean, in most cases
you probably won't end up with the four
votes, depending on how everybody feels
about the project. Um,
so
this is
I guess with the three items we had on
the agenda,
I've only seen this happen four times
now.
>> Thank you. Um,
I
I think the attorney's office is
correct. This needs to be resolved just
because it's
so unusual, but thank you.
>> Dr. Emmons.
Thank you, Miss uh Madam Chairwoman. So,
which supersedes, state statute or
bylaws?
>> Madam Chair, through you, so state
statute would supersede.
>> So, if we don't overrule the I'm sorry,
Madam Chair, through you. If we don't
overrule this, it's null and void
anyway. Would that not be correct?
>> Madam Chair, through you, that would be
correct. Basically, if if you choose to
not overrule the Planning Commission's
decision, I would then recommend that
you also deny the next item on the
agenda.
>> Thank you.
>> And that would go for any of the ones on
the agenda. Although, with this one, I
would recommend that we postpone this
item and the next item for 2 weeks, just
so it winds up on third reading with
all the other items.
>> Okay.
>> For this specific one, though, just for
Highlands, because we have the
annexation.
>> Any questions from Go ahead, Dr. Emmons.
Thank you, Madam Chairwoman. So, you're
recommending we postpone it?
>> Madam Chair, through you, just for this
meeting, yes.
Um, and that will then align
this resolution and the following
resolution with the annexation for the
through the 3,500 acres
uh because we can't amend the future
land use map unless it is within city
limits.
Because it didn't go to county
commissioners for concurrence. It only
went for comments.
Yeah. So, basically, yeah, can't adopt
the resolution without annexing the
land.
>> Okay. Um public comment, Mrs. McHenry,
did you want to
Is this the item you wanted to make
public comment on?
Okay.
Um any other public comment? It looks
like
Mr. Miller has his hand up.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> All right. Let me see here.
Okay.
>> We're on item 34.
>> Um Madam Chair, members of the
committee, for the record, Charles
Miller.
I am speaking in staunch opposition to
item 34, the resolution attempting to
overrule your own planning commission's
disapproval of the Highlands future land
use map amendment.
Proceeding with this overrule exposes
the city of Cheyenne to a catastrophic
dis- district court liability across
three specific counts.
Count one, the ghost project in the
Topanga doctrine. Under the established
Topanga doctrine, a governing body must
legally bridge the analytical gap
between the raw evidence and its
ultimate decision.
You cannot that gap today, which is
exactly why the planning commission
voted to to deny this amendment on June
1st.
Microsoft's own representative, Rachel
Irwin, formally admitted on the public
record regarding this exact campus,
Microsoft has not yet advanced detailed
design for the campus. When pressed on
the massive 3,000 acre scale, she
confessed, "At this time, we do not have
a campus of this size to pull from."
You cannot legally override your own
planning experts to authorize an
industrial land conversion for a ghost
project that the applicant openly admits
does not exist on paper.
Count two, the utilities deficit.
Furthermore, your own utility experts
confirm this evidentiary board void. The
Board of Public Utilities testified on
the live record that they have not been
approached by this developer yet. Frank
Strong explicitly confessed regarding
the sewer infrastructure. It may require
a lift station depending on their
grading. Utilizing state statute to
overrule your own planning experts to
approve the largest industrial
conversion in city history when the
applicant and utilities admit there is
no grading, no sewer plan, and no
detailed design is facially arbitrary
and capricious.
Count three, tainted education via
financial conflict of interest. The
official agent pushing this massive land
conversion on behalf of the developer is
Brad Emmons of AVI Professional
Corporation. Yet, official city records
prove that this council recently
utilized public tax dollars to enrich
AVI with a quarter million-dollar
municipal infrastructure contract.
Funneling public funds to the
developer's agent while simultaneously
advocating their multi-billion-dollar
rezoning overrule creates an egregious
financial conflict of interest that
irreparably taints this entire
quasi-judicial
proceeding. Overriding your own experts
without substantial evidence is a fatal
due process violation. Do not codify
this pre-prejudicial
abuse of discretion into the permanent
record. I formally demand a no vote on
item 34, yielding my time.
>> Mr. Miller, just to point out this is
we're talking about 87 acres in this
piece of legislation.
So,
you may want to correct your notes
there.
>> I wish you would have stopped me sooner.
>> That's okay. You had 3 minutes.
So,
okay. Um any other public comment?
>> Ouch.
>> Okay. Um
so,
hearing none or seeing none, I would
entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I would move to adopt.
>> Second.
>> Okay, we have a motion from Dr. Rennie
and a second from Dr. Immons.
>> Chairwoman?
>> Dr. Rennie?
>> I move to postpone by 2 weeks.
>> Second.
>> Okay, we also have a
a motion to postpone for 2 weeks to
allow things to catch up by Dr. Rennie
and seconded by Dr. Immons. Is there any
discussion on the amendment?
Is there any public comment on the
amendment to postpone for 2 weeks?
Hearing none or seeing none,
any discussion from the committee?
All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> All opposed?
>> No.
>> Okay, we have
this item has been amended to postpone
it for 2 weeks. Now, we'll vote on the
main motion.
>> No, we don't.
>> Oh, we don't need to. Okay, awesome.
Thank you.
Okay, next number 35 resolution. If
you'd like to read that into the record.
>> Number 35 resolution amending the future
land use map of plan Cheyenne changing
the land use designation from
agricultural rule and urban residential
to mixed use
employment and amending the urban
service boundary for probably property
generally located east of South Greeley
Highway and south of the Sweetgrass
subdivision.
>> Okay. Staff report.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
Conor White, Planning and Development
Department.
Again, this is the future land use map
amendment for Highlands, the 35 acres
changing it from agricultural rule to
mixed use employment and amending the
urban service boundary to incorporate
that land as well.
As mentioned, Planning Commission with
their vote, it was three to two.
Again, not having the four votes. So, it
is that's why you had the resolution
prior. But again, staff is going to
recommend that this be postponed for 2
weeks to keep it on track with all the
other applications.
With that, I am available for any
questions.
>> Hey.
Um any questions from committee, Dr.
Emmons?
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman. Um
I have a question for our legal Is he
still here?
>> Yes.
>> Oh, David. Um Madam Chairwoman, through
you, I'm curious as to
what the ramifications are if we were to
not deal with something that's not legal
and is therefore null and void.
Does that make sense?
Should we do that?
>> I guess I'm I'm not quite understanding
the question.
>> Um Madam Chairwoman, through you, I
guess what I'm wanting you to tell me
Let me Let's go that way. Is it doesn't
make sense to approve something that we
know is
Would that not be correct?
Mr. Hopkinson, any ideas?
>> Um
Madam Chair, uh
Dr. Emmons,
I guess I'm not quite grasping
where you're coming from with that. If
If it is moot, then just broadly
speaking and not addressing any
particular item,
sure if it's moot, then it may make
sense for the body not to act upon it if
it's not going to have any effect. I
guess I would
agree with that, but I'm not quite sure
that's what you're looking for.
>> That's That's what I wanted.
Thank you.
>> Any other questions from the committee?
Okay.
Uh we'll go out for comment. Any public
comment on this item, which is number
35?
Hearing none or seeing none,
I would entertain a motion.
>> Chairwoman I move to adopt.
>> Okay, we have a motion from Dr. Emmons.
>> Second.
>> Second from Dr. Rinne.
Um, any discussion?
We need to postpone.
>> Madam Chairwoman.
>> Yes, Dr. Rinne.
>> I'd like to move to postpone for 2
weeks.
>> Second.
>> So, we have a motion to postpone for 2
weeks by Dr. Rinne with a second from
Dr. Emmons. Any discussion?
Any public comment on postponing for 2
weeks?
Hearing none or seeing none,
all in favor of postponing for 2 weeks
say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
>> Oh.
>> Okay, this item will move forward will
be postponed for 2 weeks.
And we will go on to the next item.
We're on the last page, believe it or
not, number 36. And this again is an
item that um, the developer or the
entity is asking to have withdrawn, but
because our policies don't allow that,
uh, we will need to let this die for
lack of a second or vote it down.
So, um, can you read it into the record,
Jen?
>> Number 36, resolution over ruling the
planning commission's disapproval of an
amendment to the future land use map of
Plan Cheyenne, changing the land use
designation from mixed use residential
to mixed use employment for properly
property generally located between I-80
and College Drive and east of Southwest
Drive.
>> Okay, staff report.
>> Madam Chairwoman, this is Committee of
the Whole Planning and Development
Department.
So, again, this is part of the uh,
Southwest Drive rezoning that happened
earlier on the agenda. This is the
future land use portion.
Um, this is the overruling portion, but
because the applicant has requested that
their applications be withdrawn,
again, staff just recommends that you
make the motion and let it die due to
lack of a second.
>> Thank you. Are there any comments or
questions from the committee? Dr.
Emmons?
>> No.
>> It's all right.
Is there any public comment?
I think we're about the only ones left
in the room. Is there any public comment
online? I don't see Mr. Miller's hand
up.
Okay. Seeing none or hearing none, I
would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman,
I would move to adopt for the sake of
discussion.
>> Okay, Dr. Rennie has made a motion to
adopt. Is there a second?
Hearing none, this item will die for
lack of a second. Next item, please.
>> Number 37, resolution amending the
future land use map of plan Cheyenne,
changing the land use designation from
mixed use residential to mixed use
employment for property generally
located between I-80 and College Drive
east to South Greeley Drive.
>> Staff report, please.
>> Madam Chair, members of committee,
Connor White, Planning and Development
Department. Uh same thing. This goes
with the last item. Just make the motion
uh
to adopt and then let it die due to lack
of a second due to the applicant
requesting withdrawal of their
application.
>> Great, thank you.
Any questions from from the committee?
Any public comment
in the room or online?
Seeing or hearing none, I would
entertain a motion.
>> This one?
>> Madam Chairwoman, I move to adopt for uh
discussion.
>> Okay, we have a motion to adopt for the
sake of discussion. Is there a second?
And if for lack of a second, this item
will die. We will go on to number 38. If
you would read that, Jennifer, we're
nearing the end here.
>> Number 38, resolution overruling the
planning commission's disapproval of an
amendment to the future land use map of
plan Cheyenne changing the land use
designation from urban residential mixed
use residential mixed use commercial and
community business to mixed use
employment and removing the extension of
East Allison Road from the master
transportation plan map for general for
property generally located south of I-80
east of college drive.
>> Yeah, staff report, please.
>> Madam chair members of the committee
Conor Way planning department.
So similar situation as I discussed
before
um
with this future land use map amendment
at planning commission it did not have
the four affirmative votes it was a two
to three vote. Um so basically it was
denied by planning commission. So that's
why we have the overruling uh that's on
the agenda prior to the actual future
land use resolution.
So you would have to basically vote to
overrule the planning commission for
this resolution and that would then
allow you to
basically vote and approve the future
land use map
amendment. Um this one you can act on.
We're not postponing this one.
Um this one is all within city limits.
So this one you can act on. Um we don't
have to postpone it or anything like
that.
So that's what the overruling is. Um
it's basically to allow you to
then vote and choose to approve or not I
guess with the next item.
>> Great, thank you. Is there any question
from committee? Questions from
committee?
Hey, we will go out for public comment.
Is there any public comment?
Seeing or hearing none I would entertain
a motion.
>> Move to adopt.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Dr. Rennie and a
second from Dr. Immens to adopt.
Um is there any discussion?
Miss Dr. Winney?
>> No.
>> Okay.
Okay, all in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed? This item will move forward
with recommendation um to approve on at
Monday night's meeting. Next item.
>> Number 39 resolution amending the future
land map
future land use map of the of plan
Cheyenne changing the land use
designation from urban residential,
mixed use residential, mixed use
commercial and community business to
mixed use employment and removing the
extension of the East Allison Road from
the master transportation plan map for
property generally located south of I-80
and east of College Drive.
>> Okay, staff report, please.
>> Madam Chair, members of the Committee,
Counterway Planning and Development
Department. Again, this is the future
land use map amendment for the rezoning
that was on the agenda earlier. Um so,
being that had a positive motion, uh
staff would recommend a positive motion
on this because if you are going to
approve the BP zone out here,
the whole property should be um changed
on the future land use map to mixed use
employment.
Um it does change the master street
plan. That has been discussed with our
engineering department, WYDOT, and our
MPO. Um so, everybody is okay with what
is being proposed.
Um all these changes are happening
within city limits, so this will go to
county commissioners uh tomorrow for
comment only. I'm not predicting they'll
have any comments they haven't with the
last several future land use map
amendments we've taken to them,
especially when they're in city limit
completely within city limits.
Um
Again, Planning Commission uh
voted two to three on this, so it did
not have the four affirmative votes, so
it did have a denial from Planning
Commission. Staff did recommend approval
of this item. And with that, I am
available for any questions.
>> Are there any questions from committee?
Dr. Winney?
>> Madam Chairwoman, thank you. First of
all, I
please allow me a little license because
after we
approve the zoning, I thought of a
question in regard to it.
Um
so, through you, Madam Chairwoman, to
our staff,
if with the zoning,
um
and being changed to
mixed-use employment,
what are Will there be any buffering or
screening on the west border?
Of of required of the
developer?
>> Madam Chair, through you.
Um
so,
I'm guessing you're talking along
College.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Okay.
So,
when it gets down to where we end up
with a site plan,
um
there wouldn't be any screening involved
because you have College Drive there. If
it was directly adjacent to that zone
district, um
then yes,
there would be possibly some sort of
buffer with the BP zone.
There's still going to be street trees
where um well, there's trees that are
required still. I shouldn't say street
trees. They are required trees based on
um frontage along a public street. And
in this case, you have
a good portion of College.
Um
but ultimately, no, there would not be a
buffer that would necessarily be
required along College.
>> Uh thank you, Madam Madam Chairwoman.
Then my second question,
uh
can
Mr. White, can you review
the decision to not to remove the
extension of Allison Road to the east,
and why is that not important?
>> Madam Chair, through you.
Um
I may throw that over to Brad. I can
brief you on that.
>> Can the developer explain why this is
not important?
>> Mr. Emmons.
>> Uh Madam Chair, committee members, Brad
Emmons, uh AVI. So, uh during through
the process, we did hire a
the traffic analyst that does all of the
Cheyenne MPO work to analyze Allison
Road and the extension. And when you
take out the residential and community
areas within that block,
it is no longer needed for the
connectivity as long as we have the Fox
Farm connection at this point. That
covers
that section of Allison.
Um we would recommend, however, if the
zone change doesn't go through,
obviously none of this goes through,
that Allison Road would need to stay.
So, it's based on the future use of that
property. Um and especially when you go
to the
um College Drive four-way intersection
with Loomis Drive, and then you also
have call what that's not called
College, but when it goes through
Sweetgrass and it ties down to US 85,
all the traffic
through there just completely
changes, and so the need for Allison is
not necessary. Um we had And I would say
we've provided all that information to
the city engineer's office, and
um happy to go through it with you as
well, but just wanted to let you know
they have it. All the trip generation
models, they have all the
levels of service and all of that based
on that
running.
>> Madam Chairwoman, if I may.
>> Yes, Dr. Bonnie.
>> Um if we were sent that map, I missed
it. So, I actually would like to see
that because
I mean, Fox Farm is farther to the
north. Is that projected to go on to the
east?
>> Yes, sir.
Madam Chair, through you. So, Fox Farm
still ties in
>> the service road close to there that
>> No, cuz you have the draw is between
>> Okay.
>> So,
>> And then it's been a while since I've
seen the intersection at College and
on that corner, so
>> Loomis.
>> Yeah, I saw that one, but it's sideways
and it doesn't help so much, Mr. White.
So, at some point
>> that beforehand
>> at some point I would like, before I
vote yes on this, I'd like to see that
map or have it explained to me. Thank
you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Emmons. Any other um
questions from the committee?
Okay, any public comment here in the
room or online?
Mr. Miller.
>> Uh can you hear me?
>> I can.
>> Okay, so this is uh just so I'm uh
uh
clarified here what we're on. Uh this is
item number 39, correct? And it's for
the future land use map for the Reed
land
uh
and permanently amend the future land
use map for the Reed land and
permanently remove East Allison Road
from the master transportation plan map.
Is that correct?
>> That's correct.
>> Okay, Madam Chair, members of the
community, sorry. Charles Miller.
Um
I am speaking in opposition to item
number 39.
Um
See here. Approving this map amendment
exposes the city to catastrophic
district court liability across three
specific counts.
The count one, the traffic modeling
fiction and street sabotage. This
resolution permanently amputates the
East Allison Road extension from our
master transportation plan map. During
the June 1st Planning Commission, the
applicant's agent claimed this removal
was justified by MPO traffic modeling
showing a low amount of future long-term
employees.
Uh this is an evidentiary fabrication.
Under the established Topanga doctrine,
you must base your decisions on
substantial evidence.
Yet, Microsoft explicitly admitted on
your public record regarding these
developments, detailed design has not
yet been developed. It is mathematically
and legally impossible to run an
accurate traffic mitigation model to
delete a major public street for a ghost
project that the developer confesses
does not exist on paper.
Uh count two, statutory abandonment of
the general welfare. This amendment
officially eradicates
hundreds of acres of master-planned
urban residential and mixed-use land.
Now, just correct me if I'm wrong here
on any of these, um but your own
planning department stated verbatim in
the staff report that taking this
residential land would adversely affect
the general welfare of the community due
to Cheyenne's documented housing
challenges. It is legally indefensible
contradiction for the mayor to publicly
admit he is begging the federal
government for housing funds while this
committee simultaneously amends its
master plan to destroy prime residential
acreage.
Count three, the corporate land banking
confessions. Finally, the developer has
absolutely no immediate intent to build
here. During the June 1st Planning
Commission hearing, Microsoft's
representative Rachel Irwin was asked
directly
about this specific Reed land parcel.
Um she admitted on the live microphone,
"Yes, we do plan to land bank to have an
opportunity for long-term development."
You're permanently crippling Cheyenne's
transport regional transportation
network and exacerbating a severe
housing crisis so a trillion-dollar
corporation can hoard vacant dirt for
decades. To pass this map amendment
based on fabricated traffic models and
confessed land banking schemes is a
fatal due process violation. Do not
codify this prejud- prejudicial abuse of
discretion into the permanent record. I
formally demand a no vote on 39. Thank
you.
>> Thank you.
Any other public comment?
Okay, hearing none, I would entertain a
motion.
>> I'm chairman, and if Mr. Miller's
listening, I was just curious if he
heard the owner property owner say
they've tried for decades
to sell it as a
as a residential development and
were told that it wasn't suitable for
residential development.
>> He has muted his microphone, so.
Okay, a point taken. Any other
comments?
Okay, I would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I move to adopt.
>> You will.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I will move I will
second for the sake of discussion.
>> Okay, we have a motion from Dr. Emmons
and a second from Dr. Rennie.
Um any Is there any discussion?
Dr. Emmons?
>> No.
>> Dr. Rennie?
>> No, I
stated I
before I support this, I wanted talk to
somebody about the
road network.
>> Okay.
Okay, all in favor say I.
>> I.
>> All opposed?
Okay, this item will move forward with
recommendation to approve at the next
meeting of the council.
Believe it or not, it's only 4:20 and
we've reached our last item on the
agenda. I think we set a record for
committee meetings.
So, oh, we have
28 years. Well, thank you all for
sticking it out. We'll get this through
this one and we'll be done for the day.
Go ahead, Jennifer.
>> Number 40, resolution approving water
and sanitary sewer services by outside
user agreement for King Ranch Company LP
for lot one block one north
north range business park 15th filing
located north of I-80 west of Roundtop
Road.
>> Okay, staff report.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
Henry Kablanicky, planning and
development department. This outside
user agreement is for property located
to the west of the existing Microsoft
CYS data center and on the south side of
Happy Jack Road.
Site is approximately 34 acres and is
owned by King Ranch Company.
The outside user agreement allows the
contractor to and use water and sewer if
needed
and it also gives them a couple of
months so that work can be started
sooner. The purpose of this project is
to
to facilitate the ongoing Microsoft data
center expansion by providing contractor
parking, office trailers, storage, and a
laydown yard.
This is being done for the data center
contractor Hensel Phelps.
It should also be noted that while the
land itself is outside the city limits,
its purpose is to facilitate development
within the city. The applicant has
already received approval from the
county to utilize this site.
Conner can take any questions.
>> And
Madam Chair, if I may add as well, um
they've also actually
submitted an annexation for this parcel.
Um so basically we've got the outside
user right now. It would allow them to
start work sooner by getting this, but
they have actually submitted for
annexation which will be coming before
you next month.
Um and we'll go through the annexation
process for this parcel.
Um again, this parcel has county
approval already.
Um so they will be basically able to
develop it with the parking trailers and
laydown yard.
>> Thank you.
Yes, sir.
>> Madam Chair, committee members Brad
Emmons just was kind of kind of filled
in all the background that they had of a
county conditional use out there for the
the trailers in the uses and they just
want to hook up to water and sewer while
we were going through the annexation
process. So,
um they could get start using the water
and sewer sooner. So, happy to answer
any questions.
>> Okay.
Yes, Dr. Emmons.
>> Uh thank you, Madam Chairwoman. Just out
of curiosity, how far away is the
hookup?
>> Uh Madam Chair, through you, it's
directly adjacent. So, this the BOP
already exists on the
property to the east. So, it's basically
This is kind of a little remnant parcel
when the annexation comes through. Black
Hills owns
where their little substation is, and
then Microsoft
owns around it, and then there was this
little gap between the two. And so, it's
really just kind of fill filling in that
gap.
>> Thank you.
Uh, Dr. Renny.
>> I'm trying to to the developer's
representative, how long will it take
them, assuming they get the approvals in
a week, how long will it take them to do
the hookups?
>> Uh, Madam, through you, I believe they
want to hook it up Monday night after
the meeting.
>> Yikes.
>> gets approved.
>> Okay.
Um, any other questions from committee?
Okay, any public comment?
Think we've worn everybody out. Mr.
Strong?
You waited all this time just to talk to
us. Thank you.
>> I waited and waited for you to ask
questions of me. You never did. Um, it
through you.
Um, through you, ma'am. It will still
need to go through the Board of Public
Utility for approval, too, before they
>> won't be hooking up Monday night.
>> They will not.
>> Okay. Thank you.
Any other public comment?
I'm not seeing anything in the room or
online.
Okay, I would
entertain a motion.
>> Move to adopt.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Dr. Renny, a
second from Dr. Emmons. Is there any
discussion?
All in favor, say I.
This item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve. Um, that
concludes our agenda for today. Thank
you for your patience, and um, I am
going to look up the Tapanga doctrine.
Have a great day.